<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Apomorphic - posts</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://apomorphic.com/feeds/posts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://apomorphic.com/</id><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Final Version Perfected: An Underused Execution Algorithm</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/12/03/final-version-perfected" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-12-03:/2020/12/03/final-version-perfected</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted from &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xfcKYznQ6B9yuxB28/final-version-perfected-an-underused-execution-algorithm"&gt;LessWrong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TLDR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://markforster.squarespace.com/blog/2015/5/21/the-final-version-perfected-fvp.html"&gt;Final Version Perfected&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;) is a highly effective algorithm for deciding which tasks from your To-Do lists to do in what&amp;nbsp;order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The design of the &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xfcKYznQ6B9yuxB28/final-version-perfected-an-underused-execution-algorithm#The_FVP_Algorithm"&gt;algorithm&lt;/a&gt; makes it far more efficient than exhaustive ranking, while (in my experience) far more effective than just reading through …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted from &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xfcKYznQ6B9yuxB28/final-version-perfected-an-underused-execution-algorithm"&gt;LessWrong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TLDR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://markforster.squarespace.com/blog/2015/5/21/the-final-version-perfected-fvp.html"&gt;Final Version Perfected&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;) is a highly effective algorithm for deciding which tasks from your To-Do lists to do in what&amp;nbsp;order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The design of the &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xfcKYznQ6B9yuxB28/final-version-perfected-an-underused-execution-algorithm#The_FVP_Algorithm"&gt;algorithm&lt;/a&gt; makes it far more efficient than exhaustive ranking, while (in my experience) far more effective than just reading through the tasks and picking one&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is most useful when you have a large number of tasks to choose from, don’t have time to do all of them, and are initially unsure about which is&amp;nbsp;best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; very effective at overcoming psychological issues like indecision, procrastination, or &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@robertwiblin/ugh-fields-or-why-you-can-t-even-bear-to-think-about-that-task-5941837dac62"&gt;psychological aversion to particular tasks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently there are limited online tools available, and I mostly use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; with paper lists. Ideas (or tools) for better online execution of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; would be very valuable to&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execution is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_mile_(transportation)"&gt;Last Mile Problem&lt;/a&gt; of productivity infrastructure. You can put as much effort as you like into organising your goals, organising your To-Do lists, organising your calendar, but sooner or later you will be presented with more than one thing you could reasonably be doing with your time. When that happens, you will need some sort of method for choosing what that thing will be, and actually getting&amp;nbsp;started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people, I think, face this problem by either just doing the thing that is top-of-mind or looking through their To-Do list and picking something out. This works fine when the next thing to do is obvious, and you have no problems getting started on it. But when you have many potential things to do and aren’t sure which is best, or when you kind of know what the best next thing is but are avoiding it for one reason or another, you need a better&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That system needs to be quick to execute, easy to remember, and effective at actually having you do the best next task. It needs to be robust to your psychological weaknesses, minimising procrastination, indecision, and ugh fields. It needs to be efficient, requiring as little work as possible to identify the most valuable&amp;nbsp;task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href="http://markforster.squarespace.com/blog/2015/5/21/the-final-version-perfected-fvp.html"&gt;Final Version Perfected&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithm for executing tasks under &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is pretty simple. You can find a description of it by the designer &lt;a href="http://markforster.squarespace.com/blog/2015/5/21/the-final-version-perfected-fvp.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but here’s my&amp;nbsp;version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put all the tasks you have to choose from into one big unsorted&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark&lt;/strong&gt; the first item on the list. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t do it&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each &lt;em&gt;subsequent&lt;/em&gt; item on the list, ask yourself, &amp;#8220;Do I want to do this task more than the &lt;em&gt;last task I marked&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;#8221; If yes, &lt;strong&gt;mark it&lt;/strong&gt;. If no, &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;#8217;t mark it&lt;/strong&gt;. Move on to the next&amp;nbsp;item.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you reach the end of the list, trace back up to find the bottom-most marked task. &lt;strong&gt;Do it&lt;/strong&gt;, then &lt;strong&gt;cross it off&lt;/strong&gt; the&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning with the next unmarked task &lt;em&gt;after the task you just crossed off&lt;/em&gt;, repeat step 3, comparing each task to the bottom-most uncrossed marked task (i.e. the one prior to the one you just crossed&amp;nbsp;out).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to step 4. Repeat until you run out of time or list&amp;nbsp;items.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;, then, you perform a series of pairwise comparisons between tasks, in each case asking whether the new task is something you &lt;em&gt;want to do more than&lt;/em&gt; the old task. The “want to do more than” comparison is deliberately vague: Depending on context, it might be the thing that would best move your project forward, the thing that would have the worst consequences if you didn’t do it, or the thing you would most enjoy doing. The key thing is that at each stage, you’re only comparing each task to the &lt;em&gt;most recent task you marked&lt;/em&gt;, ignoring all previous&amp;nbsp;tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll talk more in a moment about why I think this algorithm is a good one, but first, let’s work through an example. (If you&amp;#8217;re sure you already understand the algorithm, click &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xfcKYznQ6B9yuxB28/final-version-perfected-an-underused-execution-algorithm#FVP__Why_and_why_not"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to go straight to the pros and&amp;nbsp;cons.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A long-ish&amp;nbsp;example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s say this is my to-do list for&amp;nbsp;today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start by marking the first&amp;nbsp;item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I compare it to the next item on the list. Which do I want to do more, finish the term paper or buy milk? Well, the term paper is due today, and I don&amp;#8217;t need milk until tomorrow, so I decide to do the term paper&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to item 3. I already decided I want to finish the term paper before buying milk, so I can ignore the milk for now. Do I want to play video games or finish my term paper? Well, in some sense I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to play video games more, but my all-things-considered &lt;em&gt;endorsement&lt;/em&gt; is to finish the term paper first, so I leave item 3&amp;nbsp;unmarked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, item 4: do I want to finish the term paper or work out? Well, in some sense I&amp;#8217;d rather not do either, and in another sense the term paper is more urgent, but working out is important, I&amp;#8217;ve heard it has &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neurobiological_effects_of_physical_exercise"&gt;cognitive benefits&lt;/a&gt;, and I know from experience that if I don&amp;#8217;t do it first thing I won&amp;#8217;t do it, so it takes&amp;nbsp;precedence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Item 5: oh yeah, I forgot, I need to save the world today. Damn. Well, I can&amp;#8217;t work out if there&amp;#8217;s no world to work out in, so I guess I’ll do that&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Save the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ditto for walking the dog: much though I love him, I won&amp;#8217;t have anywhere to walk him if I don&amp;#8217;t save the world first, so that takes precedence&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve finished the list now, so it&amp;#8217;s time to do the last item on the list. Looks like that&amp;#8217;s saving the world. Luckily, it doesn&amp;#8217;t take&amp;nbsp;long:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Work&amp;nbsp;out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Save the world&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;#8217;ve done the highest priority task on the list, I go back to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; to determine the next one. There&amp;#8217;s actually only one comparison I need to make: work out or walk the dog? Walking the dog can wait until the evening, so it’s time to head to the&amp;nbsp;gym.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Finish term&amp;nbsp;paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Work out&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Save the world&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, there&amp;#8217;s only one more comparison I need to do to determine my next top task: do I want to finish my term paper, or walk the dog? And again, walking the dog isn&amp;#8217;t that urgent, so I spend a few hours on the term&amp;nbsp;paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Finish term paper&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Work out&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Save the world&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;#8217;m all the way back to the top of the list! But now there are &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; more comparisons to make to decide on the next task. First, do I want to buy milk, or play video games? I&amp;#8217;ve worked pretty hard so far today, and buying milk isn&amp;#8217;t that important, so let&amp;#8217;s play games&amp;nbsp;first:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Finish term paper&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Work out&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Save the world&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, do I want to walk the dog or play video games? The dog has been waiting for hours for a walk now, and I could do with some fresh air, and I&amp;#8217;d feel guilty just gaming without taking him out, so let&amp;#8217;s do that&amp;nbsp;first:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Buy&amp;nbsp;milk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Finish term paper&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Play video&amp;nbsp;games&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Work out&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;s&gt;× Save the world&lt;/s&gt;  ✓&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;× Walk the&amp;nbsp;dog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s no unmarked tasks in the list now, so to finish I just work up the list in order: first walking the dog, then playing games, then, finally, buying&amp;nbsp;milk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;: Why and why&amp;nbsp;not&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usefulness of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; depends on a few key&amp;nbsp;assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firstly, the algorithm assumes your preferences are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transitive_relation#Examples"&gt;transitive&lt;/a&gt;, and that you can accurately assess the value of each task according to your preferences. These are pretty fundamental assumptions that will be integral to almost any list-based execution system. In reality, your preferences probably aren’t quite transitive, but hopefully they are close enough that pretending they are is reasonable. As for accurately assessing each task, well, no execution algorithm can prevent you from making any mistakes, but &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is more effective than most at eliciting your best&amp;nbsp;guesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondly, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; assumes that your preferences are &lt;strong&gt;stable&lt;/strong&gt; over the timeframe you&amp;#8217;re using it. If your preferences shift substantially over that period, such that you need to re-prioritise among the existing tasks on your list, you&amp;#8217;ll need to throw out your previous &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; and start again. This places some constraints on the timescale you can organise using a single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; iteration: I seldom stick with the same iteration for longer than a day. (Note, though, that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; can handle the addition of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; tasks quite easily, as long as they don’t alter the existing&amp;nbsp;order.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thirdly, the value of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is greatest when you are &lt;strong&gt;unsure&lt;/strong&gt; about which task you should do next, and especially when you don’t have time to do every task you might want to do that day. I find &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; most useful when I have a lot of different tasks competing for my time; it is much less useful when my time is pre-allocated to a single, well-planned-out&amp;nbsp;task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these conditions are met, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; effective method for guiding action. It is both efficient and exhaustive: guaranteed to identify the top-priority task while avoiding most of the work involved in producing a complete ranking. It is a simple algorithm, easy to remember and quick to perform. After doing it for a while, I find it scarcely requires conscious thought – but still reliably identifies the most valuable task for me to work&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest benefit I get from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;, though, is how much easier it makes it to &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@robertwiblin/ugh-fields-or-why-you-can-t-even-bear-to-think-about-that-task-5941837dac62"&gt;do important things I&amp;#8217;d rather avoid&lt;/a&gt;. There is something about a bald, pairwise comparison between two tasks that is highly effective at overcoming my aversion to difficult things. If an important but unpleasant task is nestled within a long to-do list of minor-but-rewarding busywork, it is easy for my eye to skip over the difficult task, defer it till tomorrow, and work on something more pleasant instead. It&amp;#8217;s much harder to do that when comparing the important task to each minor task in&amp;nbsp;isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; is also good at minimising &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buridan%27s_ass"&gt;time lost due to indecision&lt;/a&gt;. When presented with a menu of tasks to choose from, it can be quite hard to select a single task to work on first. When that choice process is reduced to a series of simple pairwise comparisons, the choosing process as a whole becomes much easier. And, once I&amp;#8217;ve finished with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; and selected a single winning task, there&amp;#8217;s an impetus towards starting that makes me much less prone to&amp;nbsp;procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last brief note on infrastructure: due to its relative obscurity, I haven’t found great online tools for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href="http://complice.co/"&gt;Complice&lt;/a&gt;’s starred-task system can be passably adapted to the algorithm, but in general I’ve found physical paper lists to work best. When I was at work I would print off my Todoist task lists and use those; now I’m working from home I mostly write them out by hand. This is kind of time-consuming and redundant, so if you dislike paper notes and don’t have access to a printer it might be a significant mark against &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d really love it if someone created a great online tool for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; or integrated it more formally into an existing productivity application, but I don’t expect that to happen any time soon. In the meantime, if you have ideas for existing ways to execute &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FVP&lt;/span&gt; online, I’d love to hear about&amp;nbsp;them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="rationality"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="self-improvement"></category></entry><entry><title>Ten games I love</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/11/30/10-games-i-love" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-11-30:/2020/11/30/10-games-i-love</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this all-too-solitary year, a few different people have asked me for video game recommendations. I generally responded with overwhelmingly long lists that probably did more to scare them away than anything else. But with a long, dark winter approaching and the pandemic still keeping most of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this all-too-solitary year, a few different people have asked me for video game recommendations. I generally responded with overwhelmingly long lists that probably did more to scare them away than anything else. But with a long, dark winter approaching and the pandemic still keeping most of us at home, it seems like a better time than ever to explore a few new corners of the digital world. So, here&amp;#8217;s a shorter list, in no particular order, of ten not-too-long, more-than-minimally-obscure games I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; think you should&amp;nbsp;play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Return of the Obra&amp;nbsp;Dinn&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="If I could reproduce the theme tune in writing here, I would" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/653530/capsule_616x353.jpg?t=1581420578"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, Lucas Pope made &lt;em&gt;Papers Please&lt;/em&gt;, a very stressful game about guarding the border of a totalitarian state. Then he disappeared for five years. In 2018, he resurfaced with &lt;a href="https://obradinn.com/"&gt;one of the best games I have ever played&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, the &lt;em&gt;Obra Dinn&lt;/em&gt; set sail from England, bound for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formosa"&gt;Formosa&lt;/a&gt;. Then it disappeared for five years. Now it has reappeared off the English coast, derelict, and the East India Company has sent you to find out what the funk&amp;nbsp;happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armed with a ship&amp;#8217;s manifest, a map of the ship, pictures of the crew, and a magic watch that lets you relive the last few seconds of a corpse&amp;#8217;s life (standard issue for insurance agents in the 19th century), you must identify the fate of each of the 60 crewmembers. Oh, and the whole thing is meticulously rendered in 1-bit&amp;nbsp;graphics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Poor unfortunate soul" src="https://obradinn.com/img/shots/Ship-02.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, &lt;em&gt;Return of the Obra Dinn&lt;/em&gt; is one huge puzzle – perhaps my favourite puzzle in any video game I&amp;#8217;ve played. By paying attention to everything that&amp;#8217;s going on in every scene, you slowly piece together who is who, and what happened to them. You never need to guess: every identity and every fate, however obscure, is specified by some telling detail somewhere. It&amp;#8217;s enthralling, especially once the story starts to get moving and you find out more and more about what happened to this misbegotten ship and her unfortunate crew. It&amp;#8217;s hard to say more without spoilers; let&amp;#8217;s just say that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dither"&gt;dithered&lt;/a&gt; explosions are surprisingly&amp;nbsp;beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dithering!" src="https://obradinn.com/img/shots/Book-04.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played Obra Dinn straight through in about seven hours, while bedridden with a nasty cold. My incapacitated state made me take more leaps of guesswork than I might otherwise have done, which I will regret forever: the characters etch themselves into your brain so deeply that the game is basically unplayable, so I&amp;#8217;ll never get the chance to discover those answers the right way. If you take me up on this recommendation, learn from my example, and approach this game with the patience it deserves. It&amp;#8217;ll probably still take you less than 10 hours (though no shame if it&amp;#8217;s longer!), and It&amp;#8217;s well worth the&amp;nbsp;effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Stanley&amp;nbsp;Parable&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;When Stanley came to a set of two open doors, he entered the door on his&amp;nbsp;left.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Take the left door" src="https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/images/13/oct/stanley2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/221910/The_Stanley_Parable/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stanley Parable&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a very, very hard game to review. Firstly, because it is so strange, so unlike anything except itself. Secondly, because it&amp;#8217;s so difficult to write about any aspect of it without diminishing the experience of discovering it for&amp;nbsp;yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is not to say I don&amp;#8217;t have thoughts about it! I wrote a whole thing here about all the different possible interpretations of &lt;em&gt;The Stanley Parable&lt;/em&gt; and how they all, one by one, fall by the wayside, until all that is left is the thing itself, glorious and hilarious and free. But eventually I decided even that was too spoilery, and cut it in favour of&amp;nbsp;this&amp;#8230;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Just a regular office, nothing to see here" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/221910/ss_523aa042385c6b1c8f6c9870ecffef18627d9064.1920x1080.jpg?t=1584652672"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, it&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/stanley-parable-the-spoiler-free-review/"&gt;really good&lt;/a&gt;, okay? It&amp;#8217;s funny and smart and meta in all the best ways. It handles the question of choice in video games, which really is the only new thing videos bring to the table in terms of Art, with more wit and intelligence than any other game I&amp;#8217;ve played. It&amp;#8217;s not a long game, unless for some weird reason you end up playing it over and over and over and over and over again, but who would do something like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Showing the screen room seems to be okay, everyone shows the screen room" src="https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/images/13/oct/stanley3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily the &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/221910/The_Stanley_Parable/"&gt;free demo&lt;/a&gt; does a pretty good job of telling you whether or not you&amp;#8217;ll enjoy the game, while&amp;#8230;agh, just play the demo, it&amp;#8217;s good – though not quite as good as the real&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, it is rumoured, an &lt;a href="https://www.stanleyparable.com/"&gt;expanded version in the works&lt;/a&gt;, but since that version (a) is likely to be substantially different, and (b) has been delayed several times, you&amp;#8217;re probably better off just taking the plunge now. If you&amp;#8217;re anything like me, you&amp;#8217;re unlikely to regret the opportunity to play it again in a year or&amp;nbsp;two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shadowrun: Dragonfall and Shadowrun: Hong&amp;nbsp;Kong&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Want to play as a badass orc soldier/shaman double team? Sure, why not?" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/346940/header.jpg?t=1589903402"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a setting, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shadowrun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; confuses me. It really shouldn&amp;#8217;t work. At first glance it&amp;#8217;s the worst kind of incoherent coolism, the kind of setting whose operative principle is &amp;#8220;Sure, why not?&amp;#8221;. Want to play an elf that can do awesome magic and is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; a wicked cool cyberpunk hacker? Want to control an army of mechanical drones, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; an army of spooky elemental spirits? Sure, why not? Want to fight against a nefarious megacorporation who are also powering their evil machines with the souls of the dead? Sure, why not? Throw in the kitchen sink while you&amp;#8217;re at it, might as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, it works. In some ways it works much better than other fantasy settings, because it doesn&amp;#8217;t assume that worlds different from ours must be technologically static. Magic re-emerged into the world, things changed and people died, and the world kept on going. Now it&amp;#8217;s decades later, and the dragons have realised that you can get richer on the stock market than you can hoarding treasure, and the corporations have learned which problems are best solved with technology and which are best outsourced to the&amp;nbsp;shamans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harebrained Schemes&amp;#8217; first entry into the Shadowrun universe, &lt;em&gt;Shadowrun Returns&lt;/em&gt;, was, in my opinion, not very good. But the two games it followed up with, &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/300550/Shadowrun_Dragonfall__Directors_Cut/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shadowrun: Dragonfall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/346940/Shadowrun_Hong_Kong__Extended_Edition/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shadowrun: Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, are two of my favourite RPGs. Each is in a lovingly realised setting, with gorgeous backdrops, lots of interesting missions, and – especially in &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt; – characters I actually cared about. Crucially, neither outstays its welcome, with both being much shorter than your average (gargantuan)&amp;nbsp;cRPG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="It's cyberspace...but in Asia!" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/346940/ss_9ceff2ce232d0b6b765545bd0e96ebf9992e299d.1920x1080.jpg?t=1589903402"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In gameplay and overall style, the two games are essentially the same, though &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt; is a little slicker. At the heart of both games is the classic &lt;em&gt;Shadowrun&lt;/em&gt; concept: corporate espionage, exfiltration, the occasional assassination job if you have the stomach for it. It&amp;#8217;s a nasty business, essentially organised crime, and most of the people who do it are nasty folks, but somehow the games always find a way for you to be a hero, if you want to be (in &lt;em&gt;Dragonfall&lt;/em&gt; I was; in &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;nbsp;wasn&amp;#8217;t).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;#8217;s probably worth noting here that these are by far the most combat heavy of the games on this list (though not the most explicitly violent – that would be &lt;em&gt;Obra Dinn&lt;/em&gt;), so if you&amp;#8217;re not interest in having your cyberpunk worldbuilding interspersed with mowing down armies of mech-armoured, spellslinging goons then these probably aren&amp;#8217;t the games for&amp;nbsp;you.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More important than the missions, though, is the world they inhabit, and it&amp;#8217;s here that both games shine. Both achieve what many RPGs fail to, and make 2050s Berlin and Hong Kong (respectively) feel like living, breathing places – I can&amp;#8217;t comment on the plausibility of the Hong Kong setting, but I found 2050s cyberpunk Berlin surprisingly believable, all things considered.  Neither the cyberpunk nor the fantasy tropes are especially original by themselves, but in the interweaving of the two both games find that special something that makes the &lt;em&gt;Shadowrun&lt;/em&gt; setting shine. Both also have surprisingly deep dialogue trees and character development for many minor NPCs; in &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt; in particular, I got quite invested in all the little lives going on around me in our little shanty-town home&amp;nbsp;base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Home sweet home" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/346940/ss_b6408a64a1c50c394560a5aeff02617d5adcfeb3.1920x1080.jpg?t=1589903402"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of setting and storyline, &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt; is probably the better game; in terms of combat I think &lt;em&gt;Dragonfall&lt;/em&gt; offers a more interesting challenge, though that might just be because I built my character better in &lt;em&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/em&gt;. Both are well worth your time and&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;To The&amp;nbsp;Moon&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="If you could hear the music playing you'd be hooked already" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/206440/ss_23b844b452cacfaaef177f78f99793ae527bb273.1920x1080.jpg?t=1579718439"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t honestly remember whether or not I cried at the ending of &lt;a href="https://freebirdgames.com/to_the_moon/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;To The Moon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I do remember feeling more emotionally conflicted about it than basically any other game I&amp;#8217;ve&amp;nbsp;played.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got the game in some Humble Bundle years ago. Tried it, bounced off the graphics and the gameplay style, and forgot about it for years. At some point a friend mentioned that it was one of her favourite games, and I was interested enough to try it again. Turns out, abandoning it the first time was a huge&amp;nbsp;mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setting: Sigmund Corp is a company that sells deathbed wishes. You want to be president, or marry the love or your life, or become a billionaire? Sigmund can give it to you. Just sign the contract, hand over the fee, and when you&amp;#8217;re dying they&amp;#8217;ll come and edit your memories, ensuring you die happy in the knowledge of a life&amp;nbsp;well-lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fire up the experience machine!" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/206440/ss_244339bfc260fdc2d2f4cdbe3fc3c6df0cb700ed.1920x1080.jpg?t=1579718439"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that a&amp;#8230;&lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing to do? Hard to say. It&amp;#8217;s a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experience_machine"&gt;great thought experiment&lt;/a&gt;, though, and it&amp;#8217;s excellently – and traumatically – handled&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;To The Moon&lt;/em&gt; you play as a team of Sigmund scientists, dispatched to fulfill its contract with Johnny, an old man slowly dying in a big house. Johnny wants to go to the moon – simple enough, the kind of wish you handle all the time. The problem, as you quickly discover, is that he doesn&amp;#8217;t remember &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;. So begins a traversal back though a lifetime of memories, trying to discover work out what to change to give Johnny whatever it is that he really&amp;nbsp;wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Time to find out WTF is up with all these paper rabbits" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/206440/ss_edee6b77fa9948845500b14af3db7c887a8f5819.1920x1080.jpg?t=1579718439"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telling a story backwards is not a new trope, but it&amp;#8217;s one that&amp;#8217;s difficult to pull off well, and &lt;em&gt;To The Moon&lt;/em&gt; does so with flying colours. It&amp;#8217;s a story with no shortage of Themes, which it (mostly) handles with depth and grace, if not always with subtlety. The music is stunning, some of the best I&amp;#8217;ve ever experienced anywhere, a fact made even more remarkable by the fact that it was all composed by the game&amp;#8217;s lone&amp;nbsp;developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are wrinkles. I still don&amp;#8217;t get on well with the graphics style, or the game engine. The humour is a mixed bag, sometimes charming and sometimes irritating. The game can&amp;#8217;t quite bring itself to be a pure walking simulator, and insists on wedging in silly minigames that add nothing to the overall experience. But I&amp;#8217;m willing to let all of these annoyances slide, because the thing in its entirety is so&amp;nbsp;beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Dear&amp;nbsp;Esther&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The clouds are a metaphor for my soul" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/520720/ss_c4975fc5de1b03e2df8bc5df1d573f4e5796f829.1920x1080.jpg?t=1591106858"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the games on this list, I expect &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/520720/Dear_Esther_Landmark_Edition/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dear Esther&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to be the most &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=ymmv"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;YMMV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A game in which you slowly walk around a windswept island, with no run or jump buttons, no goal except to keep going, hear what the game wants you to here and see what it wants you to see&amp;#8230;is not going to be for everyone. But at a pretty important time in my life, it was for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the various emotions you might encounter over the course of a life, the one games are least well-equipped to reckon with is sadness. Excitement, joy, curiosity, wonder, fear, anger, disgust: all are well-represented in the gaming canon. But sadness, depression, grief are slow, heavy, aimless things, ill-suited to the high-intensity engagement of most popular games. Any game that would seriously reckon with these slow, tired, lonely feelings must itself feel slow and tired and lonely: hardly a recipe for a&amp;nbsp;money-spinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless there is a small but persistent line of games attempting to deal with these kinds of experiences. Of these, &lt;em&gt;Dear Esther&lt;/em&gt; is the one that found me when I needed&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="That godforsaken aerial" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/520720/ss_4c154057e9a392d14c4ef9de6ec49adda7ff254c.1920x1080.jpg?t=1591106858"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play as a man on a desolate island, alternately scenic and oppressive. You&amp;#8217;re not initially sure why he&amp;#8217;s here or what he&amp;#8217;s talking about in his erudite-yet-roundabout narration, but it becomes clear he&amp;#8217;s circling around some deep wound he doesn&amp;#8217;t quite dare to touch. The music is beautiful, some of my favourite in gaming, expertly calibrated to the mood of the place. The first part of the game is admittedly a very slow start; but as you go on, and the narrator starts to lose his composure, and night begins to fall, the game becomes both more vivid and more intense. From about the halfway point on, I would call all of it – not just the audio –&amp;nbsp;beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Who put that candle there?" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/520720/ss_604d22b3ff0a67d09b7bf7dac1c6d3f40de56218.1920x1080.jpg?t=1591106858"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game also rewards replaying: because it&amp;#8217;s so short, because the narrator&amp;#8217;s audio is somewhat randomised so you never hear exactly the same thing each time, and because the things you learn later cast substantial parts of the earlier game into a different&amp;nbsp;light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest is spoilers. Your mileage may vary. Perhaps it won&amp;#8217;t speak to you. But it&amp;#8217;s one of my favourite games, and it&amp;#8217;s short enough and cheap enough that I think it&amp;#8217;s worth&amp;nbsp;trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Spider and&amp;nbsp;Web&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="This is literally the only picture associated with the game. It's a text adventure, what do you expect?" src="https://ifdb.tads.org/showimage?id=4%3A1270"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;#8217;t quite resist putting a text adventure on this list. There are actually quite a few text adventures I like a lot, but they are admittedly pretty niche, so I&amp;#8217;m restricting myself to one full entry, and a few links. Andrew Plotkin&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://ifdb.tads.org/viewgame?id=2xyccw3pe0uovfad"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; made the cut because it tries to do something I&amp;#8217;ve never quite seen in any other game, and does so&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, we should expect text adventures to be at their best when they try to do things that are difficult to do effectively with graphics but can be done very effectively with words. &lt;a href="https://ifdb.tads.org/viewgame?id=j6vtd2djn6o97a8b"&gt;Surreal humour&lt;/a&gt; is one example; &lt;a href="https://ifdb.tads.org/viewgame?id=op0uw1gn1tjqmjt7"&gt;creepy cosmic horror&lt;/a&gt; is another. &lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;/em&gt; is an example of a third thing: editing the narrative. Unreliable narrators are an underused trope in video games, one for which I&amp;#8217;d generally expect text adventures to have a somewhat better time than graphical games. In &lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;/em&gt;, the unreliable narrator is&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You begin in an unremarkable alleyway in an unspecified city, facing an unmarked door. Why are you here? You certainly don&amp;#8217;t have anything suspicious in your pockets that could open such a door; in fact your inventory is empty. Oh, well. You turn and&amp;nbsp;leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bright lights. An interrogation room. Your interrogator is not impressed. Obviously you didn&amp;#8217;t just turn and leave, because they found you &lt;em&gt;behind&lt;/em&gt; the door. Try&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On it goes. You get past the door. You infiltrate the facility. You turn left and burst into the laboratory complex! No, you would have been spotted immediately, and you weren&amp;#8217;t caught until later. You must have gone a different way. Try&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a hard game, sometimes viciously so. You need to simultaneously solve the immediate puzzles of espionage, while also keeping an eye out for little ways to get the jump on your interrogators. Most of the time, they catch you at it; occasionally, they don&amp;#8217;t. If you fail enough times the interrogator starts making little comments about how he&amp;#8217;d expect a spy of your calibre to be a little smarter. The puzzle at the turning-point of the game is fiendishly hard – I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure I used a walkthrough, or at least got some hints. But it&amp;#8217;s also so clever I found it hard to fault it for being so&amp;nbsp;difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most text adventures, &lt;em&gt;Spider and Web&lt;/em&gt; has the significant advantage of being free, at least if you discount the time required to get used to the basic conventions of the genre. You can run it on your command line if you&amp;#8217;re feeling hacker-y, but dedicated software like &lt;a href="https://www.electronjs.org/apps/lectrote"&gt;Lectrote&lt;/a&gt; (by the same author as the game)can make the experience a little more friendly. If you like it, good news! There&amp;#8217;s a whole little world of &lt;a href="https://ifdb.tads.org/viewcomp?id=1lv599reviaxvwo7"&gt;free interactive fiction&lt;/a&gt; waiting for you, much of it rather&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disco&amp;nbsp;Elysium&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, back to the world of&amp;nbsp;pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="I didn't say they'd be good pictures" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/632470/ss_4f5fdc3cf42feca8dafb1f7d2910ef96e62708a2.1920x1080.jpg?t=1606312997"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all the games on this list, &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/632470/Disco_Elysium/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is the only one I discovered this year. I picked it up at the height of the first &lt;span class="caps"&gt;COVID&lt;/span&gt; wave, in the midst of my worst depression relapse for years, on the advice of a &lt;a href="https://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2019/11/29/disco-elysium-offers-a-dark-mirror-to-my-mid-life-crisis/"&gt;rather odd review&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Rock Paper Shotgun&lt;/em&gt;. I needed to stop thinking for a couple of days and play something interesting. Usually when I decide to buy a new game it takes me several tries to find one that hooks me; this time, somehow, I got it in&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s actually quite easy to describe &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; in a few words: it&amp;#8217;s a dialogue-centric black-comedy not-quite-sci-fi police-procedural &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, that was quite a few words, especially if you don&amp;#8217;t count the hyphens. The fact is, while many individual aspects of &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; can be seen as quite traditional, their combination is very original&amp;nbsp;indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it&amp;#8217;s funny. Much funnier than any other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve played. I laughed out loud quite a few times, and spent much of the rest of my playthrough smirking. Most of that humour comes from the shenanigans of your player character&amp;#8217;s deeply messed up inner psyche: in &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt;, your skill points represent both abilities and facets of yourself, and the more points you put in one facet, the more liable that facet is to butt in at inopportune&amp;nbsp;moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Like here, for example" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/632470/ss_ab38615b3a1d0d4309f06772db4bd9db5c250ef7.1920x1080.jpg?t=1606312997"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put points into Authority and you become more imposing, but also more boorishly status-obsessed. Put points into Inner Empire and you get more imaginative, but more prone to tear off on wild flights of fancy. The different aspects have their own voices, sometimes even their own voice actors, and their frequent internal disagreements are very&amp;nbsp;entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the humour comes from the game&amp;#8217;s huge cast of NPCs, many of whom are delightfully catty. Because that&amp;#8217;s the second thing about &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt;: it&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;political&lt;/em&gt;. And not in the regular right-great-wrongs kind of game politics, but the grubby, down-to-earth, endlessly-argued-about, real-world kind of politics. You can even pick your own politics&amp;#8230;to some degree. I went for a combination of moderate and libertarian, but rather than manifesting as a kind of moderate capitalist, my character lurched wildly between mealy-mouthed do-nothingism and unabashed greed-is-good Randianism, to the great confusion of my long-suffering&amp;nbsp;sidekick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m actually not sure where the game makers&amp;#8217; own political sympathies lie, which is its own kind of triumph: I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they&amp;#8217;re probably self-aware leftists, but I wouldn&amp;#8217;t bet much money on it. The leftist characters in the game certainly aren&amp;#8217;t treated any more kindly than the rest; if anything, the reverse is true. The only group the game seems to have nothing but contempt for (other than the racists) are those who try to avoid politics altogether by agreeing that everyone makes some good&amp;nbsp;points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="There's also the thought cabinet, which is...hard to explain" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/632470/ss_fc6969799ebf19fd2a2c8a986c9419e053606a17.1920x1080.jpg?t=1606312997"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. The &lt;em&gt;plot&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; takes the form of a police procedural, investigating a politically charged murder in a gruesomely poor part of a rundown city. Oh, and to keep things interesting your main character has the kind of retrograde amnesia you &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amnesia#In_fiction"&gt;only ever get in fiction&lt;/a&gt;, and needs to work out who the hell he is along with everything else. The &lt;em&gt;setting&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; is&amp;#8230;odd. Unsettling. In many respects, it is a world far more like our own than the settings of most RPGs, while in other respects it is a very alien place. I don&amp;#8217;t think I would like to live there, but I cared about the people who&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gameplay&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; takes the form of an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt; of sorts, though one based entirely around dialogue and skill checks, with almost no combat in the traditional sense – no point where one set of rules gives way and another, more violent set of rules takes temporary hold of the world. Since the main turn-off of most RPGs for me is the way they scatter a perfectly good plot amidst dozens or hundreds of hours of goblin-slaying, this is &lt;em&gt;fine by me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all &lt;em&gt;Disco Elysium&lt;/em&gt; is my favourite new game since&amp;#8230;well, since &lt;em&gt;Return of the Obra Dinn&lt;/em&gt;, to be honest, which is only about two years&amp;#8217; distance. But still, it&amp;#8217;s a very good game and I strongly recommend it, especially to those of you who wouldn&amp;#8217;t normally consider playing an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPG&lt;/span&gt; but are interested in trying something different. At the very least, it&amp;#8217;s made &lt;a href="https://zaumstudio.com/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ZA&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; one of the very short list of developers I&amp;#8217;m actively keeping an eye on, waiting to see what they do&amp;nbsp;next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Primordia&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of modern-but-retro point-and-click adventure games – a world that&amp;#8217;s been undergoing a modest revival over the past decade or so – &lt;a href="http://www.wadjeteyegames.com/"&gt;Wadjet Eye Games&lt;/a&gt; is king. As a fan of such games I&amp;#8217;ve played and liked most of their line-up, both as developer and as publisher, so picking a game to recommend here was a conundrum. Their &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; game is probably &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/307580/Technobabylon/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technobabylon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a huge and sprawling cyberpunk mystery story with many characters and many – perhaps too many – creative mechanics. But &lt;em&gt;Technobabylon&lt;/em&gt; isn&amp;#8217;t my &lt;em&gt;favourite&lt;/em&gt; Wadjet Eye game. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; honour would have to go to &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/227000/Primordia/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primordia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="I don't remember what the little floaty guy is called" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/227000/header.jpg?t=1573406095"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that was a controversial opinion. Back when I got &lt;em&gt;Primordia&lt;/em&gt; (for cheap in a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GOG&lt;/span&gt; sale, as I recall), it had received mostly lukewarm opinions from critics. Many said that the story didn&amp;#8217;t hold together that well, or that the comedy sidekick was kind of annoying (both true). But I see now that it has 97% positive reviews on Steam, which is flabberghastingly high, so apparently it&amp;#8217;s not as controversial an opinion as I&amp;nbsp;thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agh, I&amp;#8217;m watching the trailer on Steam now and it&amp;#8217;s giving me chills. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; its aesthetic. That melancholic, rusty intricacy gets me every time. The humans have gone, and left behind only lost little robots and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WfbLdE3Obhw"&gt;haunting music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Welcome to Metropol, city of glass and light" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/227000/ss_3754c55faf773805be7308c3e1ac9713e5048f24.1920x1080.jpg?t=1573406095"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I should step&amp;nbsp;back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Primordia&lt;/em&gt;, you play as Horatio Nullbuilt, a lonely robot in a crashed airship in a desolate, war-scarred landscape. You spend your day scavenging parts, keeping yourself alive and trying not to think too hard about the big robot city nearby, a city that saturates the airwaves with its propaganda, a city you hate without knowing why. But one day, when a robot from the city cuts its way into the ship and steals your power core, you have to choose between joining the rest of the landscape in slow, fatal decay, or reckoning with your hatred, and your&amp;nbsp;history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s how I&amp;#8217;d&amp;#8217;ve put it, anyway. Maybe that&amp;#8217;s why they don&amp;#8217;t pay me to write blurbs for video&amp;nbsp;games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much about &lt;em&gt;Primordia&lt;/em&gt; that doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense. Almost all the robots are obviously just metal humans, totally unbelievably like us in every respect. The history of Metropol barely holds together. Many key plot points hang on slender threads of suspended disbelief. But I don&amp;#8217;t care because I love it all. I love the music. I love the mellifluous voice of the antagonist and the husky robotic tones of our hero (voiced by the narrator from &lt;em&gt;Bastion&lt;/em&gt;!). I love the decaying, rust-ridden world. I love the totally implausible culture the robots have built for themselves since the humans went (especially the surnames, let me tell you about the surnames&amp;#8230;except don&amp;#8217;t, because spoilers). I love the great old robots of the city, vast and slow like ents of steel and silicon and rust, and the ruthless political games they&amp;nbsp;play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="This is not one of those city robots" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/227000/ss_c0d5b3fbcca7d10280250f0b9f302067aa30cd92.1920x1080.jpg?t=1573406095"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m baffled that a game this short could pack so much into itself that it keeps unspooling in my memory, all these years later. Somehow, so much more of it has lodged in my memory than usual that my mind, used to reconstructing big experiences from tiny slivers of memory, assumes there must really have been far more of it than there was. But that in itself tells you how memorable it was, how well it is the thing that it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear the &lt;a href="http://www.wormwoodstudios.com/"&gt;developers&lt;/a&gt; have a new game out soon, also published by Wadjet Eye. I&amp;#8217;ll definitely be keeping an eye on that. In the meantime &lt;em&gt;Primordia&lt;/em&gt; is so old and cheap now that, really, what excuse do you have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Journey&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this blog post makes clear, there are many games I&amp;#8217;m very happy to evangelise about. But there&amp;#8217;s only one game I&amp;#8217;ve ever more-or-less forced my friends and significant others to play. Last but not least, let&amp;#8217;s talk about &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/638230/Journey/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="With a single step" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/6/64/Journey_Title_Poster.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journey&amp;#8217;s&lt;/em&gt; beauty is, I think, uncontroversial. It is also many-faceted. The style of its ruined art and architecture – some mashup of ancient Egypt, classical Islam, and &lt;em&gt;Shadow of the Colossus&lt;/em&gt; – is big and solemn and imposing, a fitting match to the solemn grandeur of the desert, and of the everpresent mountain. The game&amp;#8217;s use of light and shadow is masterful, conjuring powerful and repeating cycles of safety and danger, purity and corruption, good and evil. The music is great, especially the song that plays over the closing credits, soaringly marking your&amp;#8230;ah, but that would be&amp;nbsp;telling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Light and shadow" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/638230/ss_ed77e7844e32c4cb181ce585fa1a368285c66ec5.1920x1080.jpg?t=1598556500"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what really makes the game shine, quite literally, is the sand. I&amp;#8217;ve never seen sand like this before, in the real world or any other game. I never get tired of watching it: it glitters like a sea of gemstones, shifting colours vividly from level to level as the light changes. The game reaches its first apotheosis at sundown, when the sand shines like gold against the enormous setting Sun. Just its first apotheosis, mind – there are more to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trust me, it's even better in the game" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/638230/ss_678009919bc0a5876ec7f4e60e8ec3070c090b58.1920x1080.jpg?t=1598556500"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to its visual beauty, &lt;em&gt;Journey&lt;/em&gt; is also a masterclass in nonverbal storytelling. There is not a single word of dialogue in the entire game: you piece together the story from  abstract, wordless visions and long-abandoned murals. You need to go slowly and carefully – or play several times – to really understand what&amp;#8217;s going on, but once you do it adds a layer of once-hidden meaning to everything you see. There is no other game I enjoy watching other people play as much as&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay wise, &lt;em&gt;Journey&lt;/em&gt; is simple: a little more mechanically complex and involved than a walking simulator, a little less than any other kind of game. Yet despite their simplicity the mechanics work wonderfully. Jumping and gliding are joyful; failing and falling hurt. I was particularly impressed by the game&amp;#8217;s mechanics of gameplay and loss: you can&amp;#8217;t die, so you&amp;#8217;d think the game&amp;#8217;s enemies would hold no fear, but in fact they can harm you far more enduringly and meaningfully than in a game with higher lethality and at-will&amp;nbsp;saves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shimmering" src="https://steamcdn-a.akamaihd.net/steam/apps/638230/ss_e6d90f4cc1ce3ea73f1952d6d6f9c7e6e8657e0d.1920x1080.jpg?t=1598556500"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind, that&amp;#8217;s in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PS3&lt;/span&gt; version. For all I know the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; version has at-will saving and so has given up that particular gem of design. But! As of 2020 there&amp;#8217;s a &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/638230/Journey/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; version on Steam&lt;/a&gt;, which you should all immediately go and buy. I can&amp;#8217;t physically sit you down in front of my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; and hand you a controller, but this is me doing it in spirit: buy &lt;em&gt;Journey&lt;/em&gt;. Play it. Share it with your friends. Spread the good&amp;nbsp;word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and those other games I mentioned up above are pretty good too. Maybe check those out while you&amp;#8217;re at&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="video games"></category><category term="hobbies"></category><category term="casual"></category></entry><entry><title>Linkpost 2020/02</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/02/29/linkpost-2020-02" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-02-29:/2020/02/29/linkpost-2020-02</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A weird psychadelic poster saying &amp;quot;Secure all classified material&amp;quot;" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/secure_all_classified_material.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-44369361"&gt;has released&lt;/a&gt; an archive of old security posters. (h/t Schneier on&amp;nbsp;Security).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a unit of radiation called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banana_equivalent_dose"&gt;banana equivalent dose&lt;/a&gt; (h/t The&amp;nbsp;Prepared).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;[I]f the chief executive officer of a public company commits sexual harassment, he is &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-01-27/everything-might-be-insider-trading"&gt;probably also guilty of insider …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A weird psychadelic poster saying &amp;quot;Secure all classified material&amp;quot;" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/secure_all_classified_material.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-44369361"&gt;has released&lt;/a&gt; an archive of old security posters. (h/t Schneier on&amp;nbsp;Security).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a unit of radiation called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banana_equivalent_dose"&gt;banana equivalent dose&lt;/a&gt; (h/t The&amp;nbsp;Prepared).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;[I]f the chief executive officer of a public company commits sexual harassment, he is &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-01-27/everything-might-be-insider-trading"&gt;probably also guilty of insider trading&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8220;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;‘Like my cat, I often simply do what I want to do.’ This was the opening sentence of &lt;a href="https://sjbeard.weebly.com/parfit-bio.html"&gt;Derek Parfit&lt;/a&gt;’s philosophical masterpiece, Reasons and Persons… However, there was a problem. Derek did not, in fact, own a cat. Nor did he wish to become a cat owner, as he would rather spend his time taking photographs and doing philosophy. On the other hand, the sentence would clearly be better if it was true. To resolve this problem Derek drew up a legal agreement with his sister, who did own a cat, to the effect that he would take legal possession of the cat while she would continue living with&amp;nbsp;it.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China&amp;#8217;s Supreme People&amp;#8217;s Court is &lt;a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/china/society/article/3048042/chinas-top-court-hits-out-wuhan-police-over-coronavirus-rumour"&gt;not happy&lt;/a&gt; with Wuhan police for suppressing &amp;#8220;rumours&amp;#8221; of a pneumonia outbreak: &amp;#8220;It &amp;#8230; undermines the credibility and chips away at public support for the Communist Party. It could even be used by hostile overseas forces as an excuse to criticise&amp;nbsp;us.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of hostile overseas forces using this as an excuse to criticise China, Scott Sumner argues that &lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/authoritarian-nationalism-is-bad-for-your-health/"&gt;authoritarian nationalism is bad for your health&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The robots are &lt;a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2020-02/ru-nrd020620.php"&gt;coming for your blood&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grey seals &lt;a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2020-02/mu-gsd013020.php"&gt;clap underwater&lt;/a&gt; to show dominance&amp;nbsp;(maybe).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of seals, did you know some fur seals in Antarctica &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.com/earth/story/20141117-why-seals-have-sex-with-penguins"&gt;have sex with penguins&lt;/a&gt;? Sometimes they eat the penguins afterwards, sometimes they&amp;nbsp;don&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2020-02/uoa-goa020420.php"&gt;Gun owners aren&amp;#8217;t happier, don&amp;#8217;t sleep better at night&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221; No opinion on the research itself, but I love the&amp;nbsp;headline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miami has issued a &lt;a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2020/01/21/weather/miami-freeze-falling-iguana-forecast-trnd/index.html?mc_cid=381ea7cd0c&amp;amp;mc_eid=89ffab7a26"&gt;falling iguana warning&lt;/a&gt;. (h/t The&amp;nbsp;Prepared)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/fear-of-mentoring/"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Intimidation is the father of silence and the mother of&amp;nbsp;lies.&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?sa=G&amp;amp;hl=en-DE&amp;amp;sxsrf=ACYBGNSwBIOpuAT0QzNUZ2cYt4D5Wa37Ag:1581208360793&amp;amp;q=kengo+kuma+m2+building&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;source=iu&amp;amp;ictx=1&amp;amp;tbs=simg:CAES1QIJPlP5ZqMLVicayQILELCMpwgaYgpgCAMSKIYV8R3uHbENhxXoHfsdhRXfFN4U6TjqPuc-5zjoKuEq6T7KIvM4mSoaMHDdMiIxSV_1ARKl2K7lk5RMF6470Rd1hJLwAC9Z5Ir9-iQiUkTu9mwi32_1mowY5CNCAEDAsQjq7-CBoKCggIARIEtIZO9QwLEJ3twQkawQEKKAoWY2xhc3NpY2FsIGFyY2hpdGVjdHVyZdqliPYDCgoIL20vMGR2aDkKIQoOdHJpdW1waGFsIGFyY2japYj2AwsKCS9tLzAxX2hjdAofCgxyb21hbiB0ZW1wbGXapYj2AwsKCS9tLzAzZjBoNAopChZicnV0YWxpc3QgYXJjaGl0ZWN0dXJl2qWI9gMLCgkvbS8wMjZ5NTYKJgoTY29tbWVyY2lhbCBidWlsZGluZ9qliPYDCwoJL20vMDVoZzU0DA&amp;amp;fir=AGsU7Zou9Ip7IM%253A%252CEEZl02mgMlAvZM%252C_&amp;amp;vet=1&amp;amp;usg=AI4_-kSpnwmgW-VZMNP2pbtyfTohzQyaNg&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjKxaSVnMPnAhXux6YKHYK1CQYQ9QEwAnoECAEQBA#imgrc=gM0PX6jjZ99BrM:&amp;amp;vet=1"&gt;This building&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wh0.github.io/2020/01/02/scissors.html?mc_cid=a3c07a2505&amp;amp;mc_eid=89ffab7a26"&gt;Which emoji scissors close?&lt;/a&gt;? &amp;#8220;If you could file those parts down, you could close [these scissors] a lot more. But you couldn’t, because 📁 is the only file you can get in emoji&amp;#8221;. (h/t The&amp;nbsp;Prepared)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>Other Minds on the evolution of ageing</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/02/20/other-minds-ageing" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-02-20:/2020/02/20/other-minds-ageing</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Peter Godfrey-Smith&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28116739-other-minds"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Minds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is mostly a combination of a discussion on the evolution of intelligence/consciousness and a collection of fun cephalopod anecdotes, surprised me by having a very nice presentation of the core ideas of non-adaptive theories of&amp;nbsp;ageing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On mutation&amp;nbsp;accumulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are thinking …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Peter Godfrey-Smith&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28116739-other-minds"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Minds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is mostly a combination of a discussion on the evolution of intelligence/consciousness and a collection of fun cephalopod anecdotes, surprised me by having a very nice presentation of the core ideas of non-adaptive theories of&amp;nbsp;ageing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On mutation&amp;nbsp;accumulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are thinking in evolutionary terms, it’s natural to wonder if there is some hidden benefit from aging itself. Because the onset of aging in our lives can seem so “programmed,” this is a tempting idea. Perhaps old individuals die off because this benefits the species as a whole, by saving resources for the young and vigorous? But this idea is question-begging as an explanation of aging; it assumes that the young are more vigorous. So far in the story, there’s no reason why they should&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, a situation of this kind is not likely to be stable. Suppose we had a population in which the old do graciously “pass the baton” at some appropriate time, but an individual appeared who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sacrifice himself in this way, and just kept going. This one seems likely to have the chance to have a few extra offspring. If his refusal to sacrifice was also passed on in reproduction, it would spread, and the practice of sacrifice would be undermined. So even if aging did benefit the species as a whole, that would not be enough to keep it around. This argument is not the end of the line for a “hidden benefit” view, but the modern evolutionary theory of aging takes a different approach.&amp;nbsp;[&amp;#8230;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with an imaginary case. Assume there is a species of animal with &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; natural decay over time. These animals show no “senescence,” to use the word preferred by biologists. The animals start reproducing early in their life, and reproduction continues until the animal dies from some external cause—being eaten, famine, lightning strike. The risk of death from these events is assumed to be constant. In any given year, there is a (say) 5 percent chance of dying. This rate does not increase or decrease as you get older, but there is some number of years by which time &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; accident or other has almost certainly caught you. A newborn has less than a 1 percent chance of still being around at ninety years in this scenario, for example. But if that individual &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; make it to ninety, it will very probably make it to age&amp;nbsp;ninety-one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we need to look at biological mutations. [&amp;#8230;] Mutations often tend to affect particular stages in life. Some act earlier, others act later. Suppose a harmful mutation arises in our imaginary population which affects its carriers only when they have been around for many years. The individuals carrying this mutation do fine, for a while. They reproduce and pass it on. Most of the individuals &lt;em&gt;carrying&lt;/em&gt; the mutation are never &lt;em&gt;affected&lt;/em&gt; by it, because some other cause of death gets them before the mutation has any effect. Only someone who lives for an unusually long time will encounter its bad&amp;nbsp;effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we are assuming that individuals can reproduce through all their long lives, there is some tendency for natural selection to act against this late-acting mutation. Among individuals who live for a very long time, those without the mutation are likely to have more offspring than those who have it. But hardly anyone lives long enough for this fact to make a difference. So the “selection pressure” against a late-acting harmful mutation is very slight. When molecular accidents put mutations into the population, as described above, the late-acting mutations will be cleaned out less efficiently than early-acting&amp;nbsp;ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the gene pool of the population will come to contain a lot of mutations that have harmful effects on long-lived individuals. These mutations will each become more common, or be lost, mostly through sheer chance, and that makes it likely that some will become common. Everyone will carry some of these mutations. Then if some lucky individual evades its predators and other natural dangers and lives for an unusually long time, it will eventually find things starting to go wrong in its body, as the effects of these mutations kick in. It will &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; to have been “programmed to decline,” because the effects of those lurking mutations will appear on a schedule. The population has begun to evolve&amp;nbsp;aging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On antagonistic&amp;nbsp;pleiotropy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it worth saving enough money so that you will live in luxury when you are 120? Perhaps it is, if you have unlimited money coming in. Maybe you will live that long. But if you don’t have unlimited money coming in, then all the money you save for a long retirement is money you can’t do something else with now. Rather than saving the extra amount needed, it might make more sense to spend it, given that you are not likely to make it to 120&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same principle applies to mutations. A lot of mutations have more than one effect, and in some cases, a mutation might have one effect that is visible early in life and another effect that is visible later. If both effects are bad, it is easy to see what will happen—the mutation should be weeded out because of the bad effect it has early in life. It is also easy to see what will happen if both effects are good. But what if a mutation has a good effect now and a bad effect later? If “later” is far enough away that you will probably not make it to that stage anyway, due to ordinary day-to-day risks, then the bad effect is unimportant. What matters is the good effect now. So mutations with good effects early in life and bad effects late in life will accumulate; natural selection will favor them. Once many of these have arisen in the population, and all or nearly all individuals carry some of them, a decay late in life will come to seem preprogrammed. Decay will appear in each individual as if on a schedule, though each individual will show the effects a bit differently. This happens not because of some hidden evolutionary benefit of the breakdown itself, but because the breakdown is the cost paid for earlier&amp;nbsp;gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Mutation accumulation and antagonistic pleiotropy] work together. Once each process gets started, it reinforces itself and also magnifies the other. There is “positive feedback,” leading to more and more senescence. Once some mutations get established that lead to age-related decay, they make it even less likely that individuals will live past the age at which those mutations act. This means there is even less selection against mutations which have bad effects only at that advanced age. Once the wheel starts turning, it turns more and more&amp;nbsp;quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book discusses various wrinkles in the theory as it applies to different kinds of organisms, then goes on to discuss the question of why most cephalopods are so short-lived. &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Other-Minds-Octopus-Origins-Consciousness/dp/0374537194/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=other+minds&amp;amp;qid=1582261756&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Recommended&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ageing"></category><category term="evolution"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on The Weapon of Openness</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/02/13/weapon-of-openness" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-02-13:/2020/02/13/weapon-of-openness</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also posted on the &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/2aYBDbH9cSs3SDA7K/thoughts-on-the-weapon-of-openness"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum&lt;/a&gt;; see there for further critique and&amp;nbsp;discussion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://foresight.org/Updates/Background4.html"&gt;The Weapon of Openness&lt;/a&gt; is an essay published by Arthur Kantrowitz and the Foresight Institute in 1989. In it, Kantrowitz argues that the long-term costs of secrecy in adversarial technology development outweigh the benefits, and that openness …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also posted on the &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/2aYBDbH9cSs3SDA7K/thoughts-on-the-weapon-of-openness"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum&lt;/a&gt;; see there for further critique and&amp;nbsp;discussion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://foresight.org/Updates/Background4.html"&gt;The Weapon of Openness&lt;/a&gt; is an essay published by Arthur Kantrowitz and the Foresight Institute in 1989. In it, Kantrowitz argues that the long-term costs of secrecy in adversarial technology development outweigh the benefits, and that openness (defined as &amp;#8220;public access to the information needed for the making of public decisions&amp;#8221;) will therefore lead to better technology relative to adversaries and hence greater national security. As a result, more open societies will tend to outperform more secretive societies, and policymakers should tend strongly towards openness even in cases where secrecy is tempting in the&amp;nbsp;short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Weapon of Openness presents itself as a narrow attack on secrecy in technological development. In the process, however, it makes many arguments which seem to generalise to other domains of societal decision-making, and can hence be viewed as a more general attack on certain kinds of secretiveness&lt;sup id="fnref:cited"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:cited"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. As such, it seems worth reviewing and reflecting on the arguments in the essay and how they might be integrated with a broader concern for information hazards and the long-term&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essay itself is fairly short and worth reading in its entirety, so I&amp;#8217;ve tried to keep this fairly brief. Any unattributed blockquotes in the footnotes are from the original&amp;nbsp;text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Secrecy in technological&amp;nbsp;development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;benefits&lt;/em&gt; of secrecy in adversarial technological development are obvious, at least in theory. Barring leaks, infiltration, or outright capture in war, the details of your technology remain opaque to outsiders. With these details obscured, it is much more difficult for adversaries to either copy your technology or design countermeasures against it. If you do really well at secrecy, even the relative power level of your technology remains obscured, which can be useful for game-theoretic reasons&lt;sup id="fnref:useful"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:useful"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;costs&lt;/em&gt; of secrecy are more subtle, and easier to miss, but potentially even greater than the benefits. This should sound alarm bells for anyone familiar with the failure modes of naïve consequentialist&amp;nbsp;reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major cost is cutting yourself off from the broader scientific and technological discourse, greatly restricting the ability of experts outside the project to either propose new suggestions or point out flaws in your current approach. This is bad enough by itself, but it also makes it much more difficult for project &lt;em&gt;insiders&lt;/em&gt; to enlist outside expertise during internal disputes over the direction of the project. The result, says Kantrowitz, is that disputes within secret projects have a much greater tendency to be resolved politically, rather than on the technical merits. That means making decisions that flatter the decision-makers, those they favour and those they want to impress, and avoiding changes of approach that might embarrass those people. This might suffice for relatively simple projects that involve making only incremental improvements on existing technology, but when the project aims for an ambitious leap in capabilities (and hence is likely to involve several false starts and course corrections) it can be crippling&lt;sup id="fnref:trial"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:trial"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This claimed tendency of secret projects to make technical decisions on political grounds hints at Kantrowitz&amp;#8217;s second major argument&lt;sup id="fnref:divisiveness"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:divisiveness"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: that secrecy greatly facilitates corruption. By screening not only the decisions but the decision-making progress from outside scrutiny, secrecy greatly reduces the incentive for decision-makers to make decisions that could be justified to outside scrutinisers. Given the well-known general tendency of humans to respond to selfish incentives, the result is unsurprising: greatly increased toleration of waste, delay and other inefficiencies, up to and including outright corruption in the narrow sense, when these inefficiencies make the lives of decision-makers or those they favour easier, or increase their status (e.g. by increasing their budget)&lt;sup id="fnref:corruption"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:corruption"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This incentive to corruption is progressive and corrosive, gradually but severely impairing general organisational effectiveness in ways that will obviously impair the effectiveness of the secret project. If the same organisation performs other secret projects in the future, the corrosion will be passed to these successor projects in the form of normalised deviance and generalised institutional decay. Since the corrupted institutions are the very ones responsible for identifying this corruption, and are screened from most or all external accountability, this problem can be very difficult to&amp;nbsp;reverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, says Kantrowitz, states that succumb to the temptations of secret technological development may reap some initial gains, but will gradually see these gains eaten away by impaired scientific/technological exchange and accumulating corruption until they are on net far less effective than if they&amp;#8217;d stayed open the whole time. The implication of this seems to be that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; and its allies should be tend much more towards openness and less towards secrecy, at least in the technological domain in peacetime&lt;sup id="fnref:nsa"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nsa"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Secrecy as a short-term&amp;nbsp;weapon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Kantrowitz makes the interesting argument that secrecy can be a highly effective &lt;em&gt;short-term&lt;/em&gt; weapon, even if it isn&amp;#8217;t a viable long-term&amp;nbsp;strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a normally-open society rapidly increases secrecy as a result of some emergency pressure (typically war) they initially retain the strong epistemic institutions and norms fostered by a culture of openness, and can thus continue to function effectively while reaping the adversarial advantages provided by secrecy. In addition, the pressures of the emergency can provide an initial incentive for good behaviour: &amp;#8220;the behavior norms of the group recruited may not tolerate the abuse of secrecy for personal advancement or interagency&amp;nbsp;rivalry.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, groups that previously functioned well in the open can continue to function well (or even better) in secret, at least for some short time. If the emergency persists for a long time, however, or if the secret institutions persist past the emergency that created them, the corroding effects of secrecy – on efficacy and corruption – will begin to take root and grow, eventually and increasingly compromising the functionality of the&amp;nbsp;organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secrecy may therefore be good tactics, but bad strategy. If true, this would explain how some organisations (most notably the Manhatten Project) produce such impressive achievements while remaining highly secretive, while also explaining why these are exceptions to the general&amp;nbsp;rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speculating about this myself, this seems like an ominous possibility: the gains from secrecy are clearly legible and acquired rapidly, while the costs accrue gradually and in a way difficult for an internal actor to spot. The initial successes justify the continuation of secrecy past the period where it provided the biggest gains, after which the accruing costs of declining institutional health make it increasingly difficult to undo. Those initial successes, if later made public, also serve to provide the organisation with a good reputation and public support, while the organisations declining performance in current events are kept secret. As a result, the organisation&amp;#8217;s secrecy could retain both public and private support well past the time at which it begins to be a net impediment to efficacy&lt;sup id="fnref:shortterm"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:shortterm"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this argument is true, it suggests that secrecy should be kept as a rare, short-term weapon in the policy toolbox. Rather than an indispensible tool of state policy, secrecy might then be regarded analogously to a powerful but addictive stimulant: to be used sparingly in emergencies and otherwise avoided as much as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final&amp;nbsp;thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Weapon of Openness presents an important-seeming point in a convincing-seeming way. Its arguments jibe with my general understanding of human nature, incentives, and economics. If true, they seem to present an important counterpoint to concerns about info hazards and information security. At the same time, the piece is an essay, not a paper, and goes to relatively little effort to make itself convincing beyond laying out its central vision: Kantrowitz provides few concrete examples and cites even fewer sources. I am, in general, highly suspicious of compelling-seeming arguments presented without evidentiary accompaniment, and I think I should be even more so when those arguments are in support of my own (pro-academic, pro-openness) leanings. So I remain somewhat uncertain as to whether the key thesis of the article is&amp;nbsp;true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(One point against that thesis that immediately comes to mind is that a great deal of successful technological development in an open society is in fact conducted in secret. Monetised open-source software aside, private companies don&amp;#8217;t seem to be in the habit of publicly sharing their product before or during product development. A fuller account of the weapon of openness would need to account for why private companies don&amp;#8217;t fail in the way secret government projects are alleged to&lt;sup id="fnref:capitalism"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:capitalism"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the arguments given in the Weapon of Openness &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; true, how should those of us primarily concerned with value of the long-term future respond? Long-termists are often sceptical of the value of generalised scientific and technological progress, and in favour of slower, more judicious, differential technological development. The Weapon of Openness suggests this may be a much more difficult needle to thread than it initially seems. We may be sanguine about the slower pace of technological development&lt;sup id="fnref:sanguine"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sanguine"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but the corrosive effects of secrecy on norms and institutions would seem to bode poorly for the long-term preservation of good values required for the future to go&amp;nbsp;well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insofar as this corrosion is inevitable, we may simply need to accept serious information hazards as part of our narrow path towards a flourishing future, mitigating them as best we can without resorting to secrecy. Insofar as it is not, exploring new ways&lt;sup id="fnref:new"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:new"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to be secretive about certain things while preserving good institutions and norms might be a very important part of getting us to a good&amp;nbsp;future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:cited"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was, for example, cited in Bostrom&amp;#8217;s original information-hazards paper in discussion of reasons one might take a robust anti-secrecy stance.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:cited" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:useful"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though uncertainty about your power can also be very harmful, if your adversaries conclude you are &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; powerful than you really are.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:useful" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:trial"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impediments to the elimination of errors will determine the pace of progress in science as they do in many other matters. It is important here to distinguish between two types of error which I will call ordinary and cherished errors. Ordinary errors can be corrected without embarrassment to powerful people. The elimination of errors which are cherished by powerful people for prestige, political, or financial reasons is an adversary process. In open science this adversary process is conducted in open meetings or in scientific journals. In a secret project it almost inevitably becomes a political battle and the outcome depends on political strength, although the rhetoric will usually employ much scientific&amp;nbsp;jargon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:trial" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:corruption"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other side of the coin is the weakness which secrecy fosters as an instrument of corruption. This is well illustrated in Reagan&amp;#8217;s 1982 Executive Order #12356 on National Security (alarmingly tightening secrecy) which states {Sec. 1.6(a)}:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8220;In no case shall information be classified in order to conceal violations of law, inefficiency, or administrative error; to prevent embarrassment to a person, organization or agency; to restrain competition; or to prevent or delay the release of information that does not require protection in the interest of national security.&amp;#8221;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This section orders criminals not to conceal their crimes and the inefficient not to conceal their inefficiency. But beyond that it provides an abbreviated guide to the crucial roles of secrecy in the processes whereby power corrupts and absolute power corrupts absolutely. Corruption by secrecy is an important clue to the strength of&amp;nbsp;openness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:corruption" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:divisiveness"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a third argument, Kantrowitz also claims that greater openness can reduce &amp;#8220;divisiveness&amp;#8221; and hence increase societal unity, further strengthening open societies relative to closed ones. I didn&amp;#8217;t find this as well-explained or convincing as his other points so I haven&amp;#8217;t discussed it in the main text here.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:divisiveness" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nsa"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can learn something about the efficiency of secret vs. open programs in peacetime from the objections raised by Adm. Bobby R. Inman, former director of the National Security Agency, to open programs in cryptography. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt;, which is a very large and very secret agency, claimed that open programs conducted by a handful of matheticians around the world, who had no access to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt; secrets, would reveal to other countries that their codes were insecure and that such research might lead to codes that even &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt; could not break. These objections exhibit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s assessment that the best secret efforts, that other countries could mount, would miss techniques which would be revealed by even a small open uncoupled program. If this is true for other countries is it not possible that it also applies to&amp;nbsp;us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nsa" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:shortterm"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kantrowitz expresses similar&amp;nbsp;thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general belief that there is strength in secrecy rests partially on its short-term successes. If we had entered &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WWII&lt;/span&gt; with a well-developed secrecy system and the corruption which would have developed with time, I am convinced that the results would have been quite&amp;nbsp;different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:shortterm" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:capitalism"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various possible answers to this I could imagine being true. The first is that private companies are in fact just as vulnerable to the corrosive effects of secrecy as governments are, and that technological progress is much lower than it would be if companies were more open. Assuming &lt;em&gt;arguendo&lt;/em&gt; that this is not the case, there are several factors I could imagine being at play:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competition&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. the standard answer). Private companies are engaged in much more ferocious competition over much shorter timescales than states are. This provides much stronger incentives for good behaviour even when a project is&amp;nbsp;secret.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selection&lt;/strong&gt;. Even if private companies are just as vulnerable to the corrosive effects of secrecy as state agencies, the intense short-term competition private firms are exposed to means that those companies with better epistemics at any given time will outcompete those that do not and gain market share. Hence the market as a whole can continue to produce effective technology projects in secret, even as secrecy continuously corrodes individual actors within the&amp;nbsp;market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short-termism&lt;/strong&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s plausible to me that, with rare exceptions, secret projects in firms are of much shorter duration than in state agencies. If this is the case, it might allow at least some private companies to continuously exploit the short-term benefits of secrecy while avoiding some or all of the long-term&amp;nbsp;costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in &lt;strong&gt;degrees of secrecy&lt;/strong&gt;. If a government project is secret, it will tend to remain so even once completed, for national security reasons. Conversely, private companies may be less attached to total, indefinite secrecy, particulary given the pro-openness incentives provided by patents. It might also be easier to bring external experts into secret private projects, through NDAs and the like, than it is to get them clearance to consult on secret state&amp;nbsp;ones.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
I don&amp;#8217;t yet know enough economics or business studies to be confident in my guesses here, and hopefully someone who knows more can tell me which of these are plausible and which are wrong.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:capitalism" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sanguine"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How true this is depends on how much importance you place on certain kinds of adversarialism: how important you think it is that particular countries (or, more probably, particular kinds of ideologies) retain their competitive advantage over others. If you believe that the kinds of norms that tend to go with an open society (free, democratic, egalitarian, truth-seeking, etc) are important to the good quality of the long-term future you may be loath to surrender one of those societies&amp;#8217; most important competitive advantages. If you doubt the long-term importance of those norms, or their association with openness, this will presumably bother you less.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sanguine" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:new"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect they really will need to be new ways, and not simply old ways with better people. But I as yet know very little about this, and am open to the possibility that solutions already exists about which I know nothing.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:new" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="information hazards"></category><category term="effective altruism"></category></entry><entry><title>The Web of Prevention</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/02/04/web-of-prevention" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-02-04:/2020/02/04/web-of-prevention</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also posted on the &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/emvBqtzYYRQwGrazx/the-web-of-prevention"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Epistemic status: Quick discussion of a seemingly useful concept from a field I as yet know little&amp;nbsp;about.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve recently started reading around the biosecurity literature, and one concept that seems to come up fairly frequently is the Web of Prevention (also variously …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also posted on the &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/emvBqtzYYRQwGrazx/the-web-of-prevention"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Epistemic status: Quick discussion of a seemingly useful concept from a field I as yet know little&amp;nbsp;about.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve recently started reading around the biosecurity literature, and one concept that seems to come up fairly frequently is the Web of Prevention (also variously called the Web of Deterrence, the Web of Protection, the Web of Reassurance&amp;#8230;&lt;sup id="fnref:web"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:web"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). Basically, this is the idea that the distributed, ever-changing, and dual-use nature of potential biosecurity threats means that we can&amp;#8217;t rely on any single strategy (e.g. traditional arms control) to prevent them. Instead, we must rely on a network of different approaches, each somewhat failure-prone, that together can provide robust&amp;nbsp;protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the original formulation of the &amp;#8220;web of deterrence&amp;#8221; identified the key elements of such a web&amp;nbsp;as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;comprehensive, verifiable and global chemical and biological arms control; broad export monitoring and controls; effective defensive and protective measures; and a range of determined and effective national and international responses to the acquisition and/or use of chemical and biological weapons&lt;sup id="fnref:webdet"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:webdet"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This later got expanded into a broader &amp;#8220;web of protection&amp;#8221; concept that included laboratory biosafety and biosecurity; biosecurity education and codes of conduct; and oversight of the life sciences. I&amp;#8217;d probably break up the space of strategies somewhat differently, but I think the basic idea is clear&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key concept here is that, though each component of the Web is a serious part of your security strategy, you don&amp;#8217;t expect any one to be fully protective or rely on it too heavily. Rather than a simple radial web, a better metaphor might be a multilayered meshwork of protective layers, each of which catches some potential threats while inevitably letting some slip through. No layer is perfect, but enough layers stacked on top of one another can together prove highly effective at blocking attacks&lt;sup id="fnref:layers"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:layers"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense. Short of a totally repressive surveillance state, it seems infeasible to eliminate &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; dangerous technologies, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; bad actors, or &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; opportunities to do harm. But if we make means, motive and opportunity each rare enough, we can prevent their confluence and so prevent&amp;nbsp;catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is the Web of Prevention. In some ways it&amp;#8217;s a very obvious idea: don&amp;#8217;t put all your eggs in one basket, don&amp;#8217;t get tunnel vision, cover all the biosecurity bases. But there&amp;#8217;s a few reasons I think it&amp;#8217;s a useful concept to have explicitly in&amp;nbsp;mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I think the concept of the Web of Prevention is important because multilayer protective strategies like this are often quite illegible. One can easily focus too much on one strand of the web / one layer of the armour, and conclude that it&amp;#8217;s far too weak to achieve effective protection. But if that layer is part of a &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; of layers, each of which catches some decent proportion of potential threats, we may be safer than we&amp;#8217;d realise if we only focused on one layer at a&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, this idea helps explain why so much important biosecurity work consists of dull, incremental improvements. Moderately improving biosafety or biosecurity at an important institution, or tweaking your biocontainment unit protocols to better handle an emergency, or changing policy to make it easier to test out new therapies during an outbreak&amp;#8230;none of these is likely to single-handedly make the difference between safety and catastrophe, but each can contribute to strengthening one layer of the&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, and more speculatively, the presence of a web of interlocking protective strategies might mean we don&amp;#8217;t always have to make each layer of protection maximally strong to keep ourselves safe. If you go overboard on surveillance of the life sciences, you&amp;#8217;ll alienate researchers and shut down a lot of highly valuable research. If you insist on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biosafety_level#Biosafety_level_4"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BSL&lt;/span&gt;-4&lt;/a&gt; conditions for any infectious pathogens, you&amp;#8217;ll burn a huge amount of resources (and goodwill, and researcher time) for not all that much benefit. And so on. Better to set the strength of each layer at a judicious level&lt;sup id="fnref:judicious"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:judicious"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and rely on the interlocking web of other measures to make up for any&amp;nbsp;shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this is to say that we&amp;#8217;re actually well-prepared and can stop worrying. Not all strands of the web are equally important, and some may have obvious catastrophic flaws. And a web of prevention optimised for preventing traditional bioattacks may not be well-suited to coping with the biosecurity dangers posed by emerging technologies. Perhaps most importantly, a long-termist outlook may substantially change the Web&amp;#8217;s ideal composition and strength. But in the end, I do think I expect something like the Web, and not a single ironclad mechanism, to be what protects&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:web"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rappert, Brian, and Caitriona McLeish, eds. (2007) &lt;em&gt;A web of prevention: biological weapons, life sciences and the governance of research.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://books.google.de/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=pXQQBAAAQBAJ&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PP1&amp;amp;dq=rappert+web+of+prevention&amp;amp;ots=m4SvXne9p6&amp;amp;sig=9LhJAZ0o3ELFIwVEdlO3y325Kwo#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=rappert%20web%20of%20prevention&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:web" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:webdet"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rappert &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; McLeish, p. 3&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:webdet" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:layers"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some extent, this metaphor depends on the layers in the armour being somewhat independent of each other, such that holes in one are unlikely to correspond to holes in another. Even better would be an arrangement such that the gaps in each layer are &lt;em&gt;anticorrelated&lt;/em&gt; with those in the next layer. If weaknesses in one layer are correlated with weaknesses in the next, though, there&amp;#8217;s a much higher chance of an attack slipping through all of them. I don&amp;#8217;t know to what extent this is a useful insight in biosecurity.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:layers" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:judicious"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, in many cases the judicious level might be &amp;#8220;extremely strong&amp;#8221;. We don&amp;#8217;t want to be relaxed about state bioweapons programs. And we especially don&amp;#8217;t want those responsible for safety at each layer to slack off because the other layers have it covered: whatever level of stringency each layer is set to, it&amp;#8217;s important to make sure that level of stringency actually applies. But still, if something isn&amp;#8217;t your sole line of defence, you can sometimes afford to weaken it slightly in exchange for other benefits.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:judicious" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="biosecurity"></category><category term="policy"></category></entry><entry><title>Why We Age, Part 2: Non-adaptive theories</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/01/12/why-we-age-2-nonadaptive" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-01-12:/2020/01/12/why-we-age-2-nonadaptive</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follows from:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro"&gt;Why We Age, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;Evolution is Sampling Error&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/31/effective-population-size"&gt;An addendum on effective population&amp;nbsp;size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro"&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced three puzzles in the evolution of&amp;nbsp;ageing: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, then, is the threefold puzzle of ageing. Why should a process that appears to be so deleterious to the individuals experiencing …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follows from:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro"&gt;Why We Age, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;Evolution is Sampling Error&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/31/effective-population-size"&gt;An addendum on effective population&amp;nbsp;size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro"&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced three puzzles in the evolution of&amp;nbsp;ageing: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, then, is the threefold puzzle of ageing. Why should a process that appears to be so deleterious to the individuals experiencing it have evolved to be so widespread in nature? Given this ubiquity, which implies there is some compelling evolutionary reason for ageing to exist, why do different animals vary so much in their lifespans? And how, when ageing has either evolved or been retained in so many different lineages, have some animals evolved to escape&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I divided existing theories of the evolution of ageing into two groups, adaptive and nonadaptive, and discussed why one commonly believed nonadaptive theory – namely, simple wear and tear – could not adequately answer these&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I&amp;#8217;ll discuss other, more sophisticated non-adaptive theories. These theories are characterised by their assertion that ageing provides no fitness benefit to organisms, but rather evolves &lt;em&gt;despite&lt;/em&gt; being deleterious to reproductive success. Despite the apparent paradoxicality of this notion, these theories are probably the most widely-believed family of explanations for the evolution of ageing among academics in the field; they&amp;#8217;re also the group of theories I personally put the most credence in at&amp;nbsp;present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can this be? How can something non-adaptive – even deleterious – have evolved and persisted in so many species across the animal kingdom? To answer this question, we need to understand a few important concepts from evolutionary biology, including &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;genetic drift&lt;/a&gt;, relaxed purifying selection, and pleiotropy. First, though, we need to clarify some important&amp;nbsp;terminology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mortality, survivorship, and&amp;nbsp;fecundity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, a &lt;strong&gt;cohort&lt;/strong&gt; is a group of individuals from the same population who were all born at the same time, i.e. they are of the same age. The &lt;strong&gt;survivorship&lt;/strong&gt; of a cohort at a given age is the percentage of individuals surviving &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; that age, or equivalently the probability of any given individual surviving at least that long. Conversely, the &lt;strong&gt;mortality&lt;/strong&gt; of a cohort at a given age is the probability of an individual from that cohort dying &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; that age, and not before or&amp;nbsp;after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Survivorship and mortality are therefore related, but distinct: survivorship is the result of &lt;em&gt;accumulating&lt;/em&gt; mortality at all ages from birth to the age of interest&lt;sup id="fnref:survmort"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:survmort"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. As a result, the mortality and survivorship curves of a cohort will almost always look very different; in particular, while mortality can increase, decrease or stay the same as age increases, survivorship must always decrease. As one important example, &lt;em&gt;constant&lt;/em&gt; mortality will give rise to an &lt;em&gt;exponential&lt;/em&gt; decline in survivorship&lt;sup id="fnref:exponential"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:exponential"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Four hypothetical mortality curves and their corresponding survivorship curves" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/mortality-survivorship.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four hypothetical mortality curves and their corresponding survivorship&amp;nbsp;curves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In evolutionary terms, survival is only important insofar as it leads to reproduction. The age-specific &lt;strong&gt;fecundity&lt;/strong&gt; of a cohort is the average number of offspring produced by an individual of that cohort at that age. Crucially, though, you need to survive to reproduce, so the actual number of offspring you are expected to produce at a given age needs to be downweighted in proportion to your probability of dying beforehand. This survival-weighted fecundity (let&amp;#8217;s call it your age-specific &lt;strong&gt;reproductive output&lt;/strong&gt;) can be found by multiplying the age-specific fecundity by the corresponding age-specific survivorship. Since this depends on survivorship, not mortality, it will tend to decline with age: a population with constant mortality and constant fecundity (i.e. no demographic ageing) will show reproductive output that declines exponentially along with&amp;nbsp;survivorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Two hypothetical mortality/fecundity curves and their corresponding reproductive outputs" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/fecundity-output.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two hypothetical mortality/fecundity curves and their corresponding reproductive&amp;nbsp;outputs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fitness of an individual is determined by their lifetime reproductive output (i.e. the total number of offspring they produce over their entire lifespan)&lt;sup id="fnref:lro"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:lro"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Mutations that significantly decrease lifetime reproductive output will therefore be strongly opposed by natural selection. It seems mutations leading to ageing (i.e. an increase in mortality and decrease in fecundity with time) should be in that category. So why does ageing&amp;nbsp;evolve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What good is&amp;nbsp;immortality?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a race of beautiful, immortal, ageless beings &amp;#8212; let&amp;#8217;s call them elves. Unlike we frail humans, elves don&amp;#8217;t age: they exhibit constant mortality and constant fecundity. As a result, their age-specific survivorship and reproductive output both fall off exponentially with increasing age &amp;#8212; far more slowly, in other words, than occurs in&amp;nbsp;humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Survivorship, cumulative fecundity and cumulative reproductive output curves for a population of elves with 1% fecundity and 0.1% mortality per year." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/fecundity-elves.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Survivorship, cumulative fecundity and cumulative reproductive output curves for a population of elves with 1% fecundity and 0.1% mortality per&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the parameters I&amp;#8217;ve used here (1% fecundity, 0.1% mortality), an elf has about a 50% chance of making it to 700 years old and a 10% chance of living to the spry old age of 2,300. An elf that makes it that far will have an average of 23 children over its life; 7 if it only makes it to the median lifespan of&amp;nbsp;700.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since fecundity and mortality are constant, an elf that makes it to 3,000 will be just as fit and healthy then as they were as a mere stripling of 500, and will most likely still have a long and bright future ahead of them. Nevertheless, the chance of any given &lt;em&gt;newborn&lt;/em&gt; elf making it that far is small (about 5%). This means that, even though an old elf could in principle have as many children as a much younger individual elf, the actual offspring in the population are mainly produced by younger individuals. Just over 50% of the lifetime expected reproductive output of a newborn elf is concentrated into its first 700 years; even though it could in principle live for millennia, producing children at the same rate all the while, its odds of reproducing are best early in life. You can, after all, only breed when you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fact &amp;#8212; that reproductive output is concentrated in early life even in the absence of ageing &amp;#8212; has one very important consequence: natural selection cares much more about you when you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Natural selection is&amp;nbsp;ageist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No genome is totally stable &amp;#8212; mutations always occur. Let&amp;#8217;s imagine that three mutations arise in our elven population. Each is fatal to its bearer, but with a time delay, analogous to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntington%27s_disease"&gt;Huntington&amp;#8217;s disease&lt;/a&gt; or some other congenital diseases in humans. Each mutation has a different delay, taking effect respectively at 100, 1000, and 10000 years of age. What effect will these mutations have on their bearers&amp;#8217; fitness, and how well will they spread in the&amp;nbsp;population?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Three potential fatal mutations in the elven populations, and their effects on lifetime reproductive output." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/elf-mutations.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Three potential fatal mutations in the elven populations, and their effects on lifetime reproductive&amp;nbsp;output.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although all three mutations have similar impacts on an individual who lives long enough to experience them, from a fitness perspective they are very different. The first mutation is disastrous: almost 90% of wild-type individuals (those without the mutation) live past age 100, and a guaranteed death at that age would eliminate almost 90% of your expected lifetime reproductive output. The second mutation is still pretty bad, but less so: a bit over a third of wild-type individuals live to age 1000, and dying at that age would eliminate a similar proportion of your expected lifetime reproductive output. The third mutation, by contrast, has almost no expected effect: less than 0.005% of individuals make it to that age, and the effect on expected lifetime reproductive output is close to zero. In terms of fitness, the first mutation would be strenuously opposed by natural selection; the second would be at a significant disadvantage; and the third would be virtually&amp;nbsp;neutral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This extreme example illustrates a general&amp;nbsp;principle: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of a mutation on the fitness of an organism depends on both the magnitude of its effect and the proportion of total reproductive output&amp;nbsp;affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;— Williams 1957&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:williams"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:williams"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mutations that take effect later in life affect a smaller proportion of total expected reproductive output and so have a smaller selective impact, even if the size of the effect when they do take effect is just as strong. The same principle applies to mutations with less dramatic effects: those that affect early-life survival and reproduction have a big effect on fitness and will be strongly selected for or against, while those that take effect later will have progressively less effect on fitness and will thus be exposed to correspondingly weaker selection pressure. Put in technical language, the selection coefficient of a mutation depends upon the age at which it takes effect, with mutations affecting later life having coefficients closer to&amp;nbsp;zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;Evolution is sampling error&lt;/a&gt;, and selection is sampling bias. When the selection coefficient is close to zero, this bias is weak, and the mutation&amp;#8217;s behaviour isn&amp;#8217;t much different from that of a neutral mutation. As such, mutations principally affecting later-life fitness will act more like neutral mutations, and increase and decrease in frequency in the population with little regard for their effects on those individuals that do live long enough to experience them. As a result, while mutations affecting early life will be purged from the population by selection, those affecting late life will be allowed to accumulate through genetic drift. Since the great majority of mutations are negative, this will result in deteriorating functionality at older&amp;nbsp;ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our elves are sadly doomed to lose their immortality, unless something very weird is happening to cause them to keep it. Mutations impairing survival and reproduction early in life will be strenuously removed by natural selection, but those causing impairments later in life will accumulate, leading to a progressive increase in mortality and decline in fecundity. This might seem bad enough, but unfortunately there is more bad news on the horizon &amp;#8212; because this isn&amp;#8217;t the only way that nonadaptive ageing can&amp;nbsp;evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Perverse&amp;nbsp;trade-offs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine now that instead of a purely negative, Huntingdon-like mutation arising in our ageless elf population, a mutation arose that provided some fitness benefit early in life at the cost of some impairment later; perhaps promoting more investment in rapid growth and less in self-repair, or disposing the bearer more towards risky fights for mates. How would &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; new mutation behave in the&amp;nbsp;population?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer depends on the magnitude of the early-life benefit granted by the mutation, as well as of its later-life cost. However, we already saw that in weighing this trade-off natural selection cares far more about fitness in early life than in later life; as such, even a mutation whose late-life cost far exceeded its early-life benefit in magnitude could be good for overall lifetime fitness, and hence have an increased chance of spreading and becoming fixed in the population. Over time, the accumulation of mutations like this could lead to ever-more-severe ageing in the population, even as the overall fitness of individuals in the population continues to&amp;nbsp;increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second scenario, in which the same mutation provides a benefit at one point in life and a cost at another, is known as &lt;em&gt;antagonistic pleiotropy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:pleiotropy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:pleiotropy"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It differs from the &lt;em&gt;mutation accumulation&lt;/em&gt; theory of ageing outlined above in that, while in the former case ageing arises primarily through genetic drift acting on late-life-affecting deleterious mutations, the latter proposes that ageing arises as a non-adaptive &lt;em&gt;side effect&lt;/em&gt; of a fitness-increasing process. Both theories are &amp;#8220;non-adaptive&amp;#8221; in that the ageing that results is not in itself good for fitness, and both depend on the same basic insight: due to inevitably declining survivorship with age, the fitness effect of a change in survival or reproduction tends to decline as the age at which it takes effect&amp;nbsp;increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mutation accumulation and antagonistic pleiotropy have historically represented the two big camps of ageing theorists, and the theories have traditionally been regarded as being in opposition to each other. I&amp;#8217;ve never really understood why, though: the basic insight required to understand both theories is the same, and conditions that gave rise to ageing via mutation accumulation could easily also give rise to additional ageing via antagonistic pleiotropy&lt;sup id="fnref:comparison"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:comparison"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Importantly, both theories give the same kinds of answers to the other two key questions of ageing I discussed last time: why do lifespans differ between species, and why do some animals escape ageing&amp;nbsp;altogether?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It&amp;#8217;s the mortality,&amp;nbsp;stupid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As explanations of ageing, both mutation accumulation and antagonistic pleiotropy depend on &lt;em&gt;extrinsic mortality&lt;/em&gt;; that is, probability of death arising from environmental factors like predation or starvation. As long as extrinsic mortality is nonzero, survivorship will decline monotonically with age, resulting (all else equal) in weaker and weaker selection agains deleterious mutations affecting later ages. The higher the extrinsic mortality, the faster the decline in survivorship with age, and the more rapid the corresponding decline in selection&amp;nbsp;strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Age-specific survivorship as a function of different levels of constant extrinsic mortality. Higher mortality results in a faster exponential decline in survivorship." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/extrinsic-mortality.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Age-specific survivorship as a function of different levels of constant extrinsic&amp;nbsp;mortality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, lower extrinsic mortality will generally result in slower ageing: your chance of surviving to a given age is higher, so greater functionality at that age is more valuable, resulting in a stronger selection pressure to maintain that&amp;nbsp;functionality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the basic explanation for why bats live so much longer than mice despite being so similar: they can fly, which protects them from predators, which reduces their extrinsic&amp;nbsp;mortality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The box plot from part 1 of this series, showing that bat species have much longer maximum lifespans than mice species. All data obtained from the AnAge database." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/bats_mice.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see something similar if you compare all birds and all mammals, controlling for body size (being larger also makes it harder to eat&amp;nbsp;you):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scatterplots of bird and mammal maximum lifespans vs adult body weight from the AnAge database, with central tendencies fit in R using local polynomial regression (LOESS). Bird species tend to have longer lifespans than mammal species of similar body weight." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/birds_mammals.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Scatterplots of bird and mammal maximum lifespans vs adult body weight from the AnAge database, with central tendencies fit in R using local polynomial regression (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOESS&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to body size and flight, you are also likely to have a longer lifespan if you are&lt;sup id="fnref:partridge"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:partridge"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arboreal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burrowing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poisonous&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Armoured&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these factors share the property of making it harder to predate you, reducing extrinsic mortality. In many species, females live longer than males even in captivity: males are more likely to (a) be brightly coloured or otherwise ostentatious, increasing predation, and (b) engage in fights and other risky behaviour that increases the risk of injury. I&amp;#8217;d predict that other factors that reduce extrinsic mortality in the wild (e.g. better immune systems, better wound healing) would similarly correlate with longer lifespans in safe&amp;nbsp;captivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, then, is the primary explanation non-adaptive ageing theories give for differences in rates of ageing between species: differences in extrinsic mortality. Mortality can&amp;#8217;t explain everything, though: in particular, since mortality is always positive, resulting in strictly decreasing survivorship with increasing age, it can&amp;#8217;t explain species that don&amp;#8217;t age at all, or even age in reverse (with lower intrinsic mortality at higher&amp;nbsp;ages). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s difficult to come up with a general theory for non-ageing species, many of which have quite ideosyncratic biology; one might say that all ageing species are alike, but every non-ageing species is non-ageing in its own way. But one way to get some of the way there is to notice that mortality/survivorship isn&amp;#8217;t the only thing affecting age-specific reproductive output; age-specific fecundity also plays a crucial role. If fecundity increases in later ages, this can counterbalance, or even occasionally outweigh, the decline in survivorship and maintain the selective value of later&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mammals and birds tend to grow, reach maturity, and stop growing. Conversely, many reptile and fish species keep growing throughout their lives. As you get bigger, you can not only defend yourself better (reducing your extrinsic mortality), but also lay more eggs. As a result, fecundity in these species increases over time, resulting – sometimes – in delayed or even nonexistent&amp;nbsp;ageing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The box plot from part 1 of this series, showing that bat species have much longer maximum lifespans than mice species. All data obtained from the AnAge database." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/tortoise-ageing.png" height=250px&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mortality (red) and fertility (blue) curves from the desert tortoise, showing declining mortality with time. Adapted from Fig. 1 of &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature12789"&gt;Jones et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;#8217;s one way a species could achieve minimal/negative senescence under non-adaptive theories of ageing: ramp up your fecundity to counteract the drop in survivorship. Another way would be to be under some independent selection pressure to develop systems (like &lt;em&gt;really good&lt;/em&gt; tissue regeneration) that incidentally also counteract the ageing process. Overall, though, it seems to be hard to luck yourself into a situation that avoids the inexorable decline in selective value imposed by falling survivorship, and non-ageing animal species are correspondingly&amp;nbsp;rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time in this series, we&amp;#8217;ll talk about the other major group of theories of ageing: adaptive ageing theories. This post will probably be quite a long time coming since I don&amp;#8217;t know anything about adaptive theories right now and will have to actually do some research. So expect a few other posts on different topics before I get around to talking about the more heterodox side of the theoretical biology of&amp;nbsp;ageing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:survmort"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In discrete time, the survivorship function of a cohort will be the product of instantaneous survival over all preceding time stages; in continuous time, it is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Product_integral"&gt;product integral&lt;/a&gt; of instantaneous survival up to the age of interest. Instantaneous survival is the probability of surviving at a given age, and thus is equal to 1 minus the mortality at that age.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:survmort" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:exponential"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exponential in continuous time; geometric in discrete time.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:exponential" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:repout"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reproductive output &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r_a\)&lt;/span&gt; at some age &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; is therefore equal to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(f_a \cdot s_a\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(f\)&lt;/span&gt; is fecundity and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(s\)&lt;/span&gt; is survivorship. Since survivorship is determined by mortality, reproductive output can also be expressed as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r_a = f_a \cdot \int_0^a m_x \:\mathrm{d}x\)&lt;/span&gt; (in continuous time) or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r_a = f_a \cdot \prod_{k=0}^am_k\)&lt;/span&gt; (in discrete time).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:repout" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:lro"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lifetime reproductive output is equal to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\int_0^\infty r_a \:\mathrm{d}a\)&lt;/span&gt; (in continuous time) or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sum_{a=0}^\infty r_a\)&lt;/span&gt; (in discrete time), where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r_a\)&lt;/span&gt; is the age-specific reproductive output at age &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:lro" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:williams"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Williams (1957) &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 11(4): 398-411.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:williams" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:pleiotropy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleiotropy"&gt;Pleiotropy&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; is the phenomenon whereby a gene or mutation exerts effects of multiple different aspects of biology simultaneously: different genetic pathways, developmental stages, organ systems, &lt;em&gt;et cetera&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Antagonistic&lt;/em&gt; pleiotropy is pleiotropy that imposes competing fitness effects, increasing fitness in one way while decreasing it in another.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:pleiotropy" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:comparison"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of the two is likely to predominate depends on factors like the &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;relative strength of selection and drift&lt;/a&gt; (which is heavily dependent on effective population size) and the commonness of mutations that cause effects of the kind proposed by antagonistic pleiotropy.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:comparison" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:partridge"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My source for this is personal communication with Linda Partridge, one of the directors at my institute and one of the most eminent ageing scientists in the world. I&amp;#8217;m happy to see any of these points contested if people think they have better evidence than an argument from authority.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:partridge" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="ageing"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="evolution"></category></entry><entry><title>Linkpost 2020/01</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2020/01/10/linkpost-2020-01" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2020-01-10:/2020/01/10/linkpost-2020-01</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year! More links abound. As always, these are &amp;#8220;new&amp;#8221; only in the sense that I read them recently; some of them are actually quite&amp;nbsp;old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More on the Blackmail Paradox: &lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/should-blackmail-be-legal/"&gt;David Henderson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/2019/02/checkmate-on-blackmail.html"&gt;Robin Hanson&lt;/a&gt; in favour of legalising blackmail, &lt;a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2019/02/why-should-blackmail-be-illegal.html"&gt;Tyler Cowen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/against-blackmail/"&gt;Scott Sumner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sideways-view.com/2019/06/02/checkmate-on-blackmail/"&gt;Paul Christiano&lt;/a&gt; against …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year! More links abound. As always, these are &amp;#8220;new&amp;#8221; only in the sense that I read them recently; some of them are actually quite&amp;nbsp;old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More on the Blackmail Paradox: &lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/should-blackmail-be-legal/"&gt;David Henderson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/2019/02/checkmate-on-blackmail.html"&gt;Robin Hanson&lt;/a&gt; in favour of legalising blackmail, &lt;a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2019/02/why-should-blackmail-be-illegal.html"&gt;Tyler Cowen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.econlib.org/against-blackmail/"&gt;Scott Sumner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sideways-view.com/2019/06/02/checkmate-on-blackmail/"&gt;Paul Christiano&lt;/a&gt; against. Hanson has written a lot on this; see the linked post for extra links if you want to go digging. Currently I feel the theoretical arguments probably support legalising blackmail, but this feels like one of those &lt;a href="http://scholars-stage.blogspot.com/2018/08/tradition-is-smarter-than-you-are.html"&gt;Secret-Of-Our-Success&lt;/a&gt;-y cases where tradition says blackmail should be illegal and we don&amp;#8217;t have a compelling enough case to risk screwing around with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aumann%27s_agreement_theorem"&gt;Aumann&amp;#8217;s agreement theorem&lt;/a&gt;, should you persist in &lt;a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/2007/01/disagree_with_s.html"&gt;disagreeing&lt;/a&gt; with a painted rock? Should you &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/jrLkMFd88b4FRMwC6/don-t-double-crux-with-suicide-rock"&gt;double-crux&lt;/a&gt; with&amp;nbsp;one?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;However, it is unfortunate that for billions of people worldwide, the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.06709.pdf"&gt;quadratic formula&lt;/a&gt; is also their first (and perhaps only) experience of a rather complicated formula which they must memorize. Countless mnemonic techniques abound, from stories of negative bees considering whether or not to go to a radical party, to songs set to the tune of &lt;em&gt;Pop Goes the Weasel&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;m &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/My8Wit9Aa49qDKpab/should-i-floss"&gt;pretty confused&lt;/a&gt; about flossing and I think you should be&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A classic in observer selection effects from Nick Bostrom: &lt;a href="https://plus.maths.org/issue17/features/traffic/2pdf/index.html/op.pdf"&gt;cars in the next lane really do go faster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rather than steal a load of cool links from another linkpost, &lt;a href="https://medium.com/fluxx-studio-notes/52-things-i-learned-in-2019-8ee483e6c816"&gt;here&amp;#8217;s the post itself&lt;/a&gt;. I can&amp;#8217;t vouch for their epistemic standards&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;a href="https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2016/dp-pd/dt-td/Rp-eng.cfm?LANG=E&amp;amp;APATH=3&amp;amp;DETAIL=0&amp;amp;DIM=0&amp;amp;FL=A&amp;amp;FREE=0&amp;amp;GC=0&amp;amp;GID=0&amp;amp;GK=0&amp;amp;GRP=1&amp;amp;PID=110180&amp;amp;PRID=10&amp;amp;PTYPE=109445&amp;amp;S=0&amp;amp;SHOWALL=0&amp;amp;SUB=888&amp;amp;Temporal=2016,2017&amp;amp;THEME=118&amp;amp;VID=0&amp;amp;VNAMEE=&amp;amp;VNAMEF="&gt;at least 4,500&lt;/a&gt; speakers of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kannada"&gt;Kannada&lt;/a&gt; in Canada. All of whom are presumably &lt;em&gt;delighted&lt;/em&gt; that you&amp;#8217;ve brought up how funny that&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wikipedia has a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Aluminium/Spelling"&gt;dedicated talk page&lt;/a&gt; for arguing about the spelling of alumin(i)um. I don&amp;#8217;t have strong feelings about it&lt;sup id="fnref:lie"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:lie"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it&amp;#8217;s undeniably entertaining. See also Wikipedia&amp;#8217;s list of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Lamest_edit_wars"&gt;lamest edit wars&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A university in Serbia is &lt;a href="https://researchprofessionalnews.com/rr-news-europe-universities-2019-12-serbian-university-accused-of-plagiarising-ethics-code/"&gt;accused&lt;/a&gt; of plagiarising a research ethics code from another university. On the one hand, this is obviously pretty funny, but on the other if I&amp;#8217;d produced a research ethics code I thought was good I think I&amp;#8217;d want as many people as possible to copy it, with or without&amp;nbsp;credit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve seen some bad websites in my time, but &lt;a href="http://www.applet-magic.com/samplemax4.htm"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; achieves the dubious feat of being genuinely physically painful to read. I&amp;#8217;m not sure why I&amp;#8217;m sharing&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;British naming habits have &lt;a href="https://capx.co/britain-is-no-longer-a-nation-of-nigels/"&gt;changed a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the last 30&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Gelman &lt;a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2019/12/20/the-opposite-of-black-box-is-not-white-box-its/"&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt; that the opposite of &amp;#8220;black box&amp;#8221; is not, in fact, white&amp;nbsp;box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I always vaguely assumed that &amp;#8220;never send to know for whom the bell tolls; it tolls for thee&amp;#8221; was some sort of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memento_mori"&gt;memento mori&lt;/a&gt; thing, but it turns out I was totally wrong about this, as reading the &lt;a href="https://web.cs.dal.ca/~johnston/poetry/island.html"&gt;whole poem&lt;/a&gt; makes clear. I might memorise this one. I also never realised before that &amp;#8220;for whom the bell tolls&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;no man is an island&amp;#8221; are quotes from the same poem, so &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=TIL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TIL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:lie"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lie, but it&amp;#8217;s one I endorse.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:lie" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>An addendum on effective population size</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/31/effective-population-size" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-12-31:/2019/12/31/effective-population-size</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follows from:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;Evolution is Sampling&amp;nbsp;Error&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems a lot of people either missed my footnotes in the last post about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_population_size"&gt;effective population size&lt;/a&gt;, or noticed them, read them and were confused&lt;sup id="fnref:footnotes"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:footnotes"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I think the second response is reasonable; for non-experts, the concept of effective population size is legitimately …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follows from:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;Evolution is Sampling&amp;nbsp;Error&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems a lot of people either missed my footnotes in the last post about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_population_size"&gt;effective population size&lt;/a&gt;, or noticed them, read them and were confused&lt;sup id="fnref:footnotes"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:footnotes"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I think the second response is reasonable; for non-experts, the concept of effective population size is legitimately fairly confusing. So I thought I&amp;#8217;d follow up with a quick addendum about what effective population size is and why we use it. Since I&amp;#8217;m not a population geneticist by training this should also be a useful reminder for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of biology that deals with the evolutionary dynamics of populations &amp;#8212; how mutations arise and spread, how allele frequencies shift over time through drift and selection, how alleles flow between partially-isolated populations &amp;#8212; is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Population_genetics"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;population genetics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;#8220;PopGen&amp;#8221; differs from most of biology in that its foundations are primarily hypothetico-deductive rather than empirical: one begins by proposing some simple model of how evolution works in a population, then derives the mathematical consequences of those initial assumptions. A very large and often very beautiful edifice of theory has been constructed from these initial axioms, often yielding surprising and interesting&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population geneticists can therefore say a great deal about the evolution of a population, &lt;em&gt;provided&lt;/em&gt; it meets some simplifying assumptions. Unfortunately, real populations often violate these assumptions, often dramatically so. When this happens, the population becomes dramatically harder to model productively, and the maths becomes dramatically more complicated and messy. It would therefore be very useful if we could find a way to usefully model more complex real populations using the models developed for the simple&amp;nbsp;cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, just such a hack exists. Many important ways in which real populations deviate from ideal assumptions cause the population to behave roughly like an idealised population of a different (typically smaller) size. This being the case, we can try to estimate the size of the idealised population that would best approximate the behaviour of the real population, then model the behaviour of that (smaller, idealised) population instead. The size of the idealised population that causes it to best approximate the behaviour of the real population is that real population&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;effective&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various ways in which deviations from the ideal assumptions of population genetics can cause a population to act as though it were smaller – i.e. to have an effective size (often denoted &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e\)&lt;/span&gt;) that is smaller than its actual census size – but two of the most important are non-constant population size and, for sexual species, nonrandom mating. According to &lt;a href="https://public.wsu.edu/~gomulki/mathgen/materials/gillespie_book.pdf"&gt;Gillespie (1998)&lt;/a&gt;, who I&amp;#8217;m using as my introductory source here, fluctuations in population size are often by far the most important&amp;nbsp;factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of some of the key equations of population genetics, a population whose size fluctuates between generations will behave like a population whose constant size is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmonic_mean"&gt;harmonic mean&lt;/a&gt; of the fluctuating sizes. Since the harmonic mean is much more sensitive to small values than the arithmetic mean, this means a population that starts large, shrinks to a small size and then grows again will have a much smaller effective size than one that remains large&lt;sup id="fnref:bottleneck"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bottleneck"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Transient &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Population_bottleneck"&gt;population bottlenecks&lt;/a&gt; can therefore have dramatic effects on the evolutionary behaviour of a&amp;nbsp;population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many natural populations fluctuate wildly in size over time, both cyclically and as a result of one-off events, leading to effective population sizes much smaller than would be expected if population size were reasonably constant. In particular, the human population as a whole has been through &lt;a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/full/10.1098/rspb.2009.1473"&gt;multiple bottlenecks&lt;/a&gt; in its history, as well as many more local bottlenecks and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founder_effect#Among_human_populations"&gt;founder effects&lt;/a&gt; occurring in particular human populations, and has recently undergone an extremely rapid &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_population_estimates#/media/File:Population_curve.svg"&gt;surge&lt;/a&gt; in population size. It should therefore not be too surprising that the human &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;em&gt;dramatically&lt;/em&gt; smaller than the census size; estimates vary pretty widely, but as I said in the footnotes to the last post, tend to be roughly on the order of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(10^4\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sexual populations, skewed sex ratios and other forms of nonrandom mating will also tend to reduce the effective size of a population, though less dramatically&lt;sup id="fnref:sex_ratio"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sex_ratio"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; I don&amp;#8217;t want to go into too much detail here since I haven&amp;#8217;t talked so much about sexual populations&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of these and other factors, then, the effective sizes of natural populations is often much smaller than their actual census sizes. Since genetic drift is &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error"&gt;stronger&lt;/a&gt; in populations with smaller effective sizes, that means we should expect populations to be much more &amp;#8220;drifty&amp;#8221; than you would expect if you just looked at their census sizes. As a result, evolution is typically more dominated by drift, and less by selection, than would be the case for an idealised population of equivalent (census)&amp;nbsp;size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:footnotes"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson 1: Always read the footnotes.
Lesson 2: Never assume people will read the footnotes.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:footnotes" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bottleneck"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple example, imagine a population that begins at size 1000 for 4 generations, then is culled to size 10 for 1 generation, then returns to size 1000 for another 5 generations. The resulting effective population size will be: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e = \frac{10}{\frac{9}{1000} + \frac{1}{10}} \approx 91.4\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A one-generation bottleneck therefore cuts the effective size of the population by an order of magnitude.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bottleneck" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sex_ratio"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="https://public.wsu.edu/~gomulki/mathgen/materials/gillespie_book.pdf"&gt;Gillespie&lt;/a&gt; again, In the most basic case of a population with two sexes, the effective population size is given by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e = \left(\frac{4\alpha}{(1+\alpha)^2}\right)\times N\)&lt;/span&gt;, where alpha is the ratio of females to males in the population. A population with twice as many males as females (or vice-versa) will have an &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e\)&lt;/span&gt; about 90% the size of its census population size; a tenfold difference between the sexes will result in an &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(N_e\)&lt;/span&gt; about a third the size of the census size. Humans have a fairly even sex ratio so this particular effect won&amp;#8217;t be very important in our case, though other kinds of nonrandom mating might well be.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sex_ratio" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="evolution"></category><category term="statistics"></category></entry><entry><title>Linkpost 12/2019</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/13/linkpost-12-2019" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-12-13:/2019/12/13/linkpost-12-2019</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some more links I read recently that I thought were cool. No guarantees any of them are actually &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; in an absolute sense; if it&amp;#8217;s relevant, make sure to check the date before using them in an argument or&amp;nbsp;something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://volokh.com/2012/08/21/blackmail/"&gt;blackmail paradox&lt;/a&gt; is my current favourite …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some more links I read recently that I thought were cool. No guarantees any of them are actually &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; in an absolute sense; if it&amp;#8217;s relevant, make sure to check the date before using them in an argument or&amp;nbsp;something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://volokh.com/2012/08/21/blackmail/"&gt;blackmail paradox&lt;/a&gt; is my current favourite thing in common law – to the extent that I&amp;#8217;m now very open to the possibility that blackmail shouldn&amp;#8217;t be illegal, or perhaps even be considered a thing. (I mean, probably that&amp;#8217;s a terrible idea, but I&amp;#8217;m honestly not really sure&amp;nbsp;why.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.overcomingbias.com/2018/11/vulnerable-world-hypothesis.html"&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; by Robin Hanson both gives a nice counterargument to the Bostromian Vulnerable World thesis and illustrates what happens what the world would be like if Nick Bostrom were attacked by a swarm of rabid ellipses. And also quotes &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anderssandberg/status/1063732784055881728"&gt;this bombshell tweet&lt;/a&gt; from Anders Sandberg in 2018, which I&amp;#8217;m amazed hasn&amp;#8217;t seen more&amp;nbsp;play.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I really like &lt;a href="https://cs.nyu.edu/faculty/davise/papers/WinogradSchemas/WSCollection.html"&gt;Winograd schemas&lt;/a&gt;, a form of linguistic puzzle that humans find trivial but machines find challenging; in 2016 the best-performing system managed 58%&amp;nbsp;accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been thinking about information hazards a lot lately; maybe I shouldn&amp;#8217;t have told you that. Anyway, for countervailing views, check out &lt;a href="https://80000hours.org/podcast/episodes/bruce-schneier-security-secrets-and-surveillance/"&gt;Bruce Schneier&amp;#8217;s interview with 80,000 Hours&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/CoXauRRzWxtsjhsj6/terrorism-tylenol-and-dangerous-information"&gt;this post on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like first-past-the-post voting, pre-performance competition for public resources is an intuitively appealing idea that &lt;a href="https://www.econtalk.org/giving-away-money-an-economists-guide-to-political-life"&gt;turns out to work horrendously badly&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212; in this case, eating up vast amounts of time and money, most of which is wasted. That it also happens to be the way we allocate almost all of our scientific funding might therefore be considered something of a disaster. &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/1/18/18183939/science-funding-grant-lotteries-research"&gt;This Vox piece&lt;/a&gt; does a good job laying out the case for one of many much-better alternatives (grant lotteries), though it does kinda pivot away into weak-sauce objections at the end. (h/t Vlad Sitalo for the EconTalk link, which I was struggling to find in the&amp;nbsp;archives.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNA&lt;/span&gt; can hold over 200 petabytes of data per gram. Why not &lt;a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2017/03/dna-could-store-all-worlds-data-one-room"&gt;use it for long-term storage&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am a fan of Stephan Guyenet and am pretty strongly convinced by his scepticism of the &amp;#8220;woo fats boo carbs&amp;#8221; narrative that seems to have taken over in many circles these days. &lt;a href="https://eatrx.com/why-are-some-people-carboholics/"&gt;Here he is&lt;/a&gt; pointing out that, actually, fat seems to be at least as addictive as sugar. (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NB&lt;/span&gt;: I think I might have actually got this one from an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;linkpost.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard is setting up a &lt;a href="https://embeddedethics.seas.harvard.edu/"&gt;research/teaching program&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;#8220;Embedded EthiCS&amp;#8221;: because it&amp;#8217;s a collaboration between the philosophy and computer science departments &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;? It&amp;#8217;s probably a good thing that this exists, but I&amp;#8217;m not sure how I feel about august institutions choosing their naming conventions based on&amp;nbsp;puns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ada Lovelace&amp;#8217;s reputation is somewhat fraught these days, caught between all those people who want to claim her as &amp;#8220;the world&amp;#8217;s first computer programmer&amp;#8221; and splash her name everywhere, and people who think she&amp;#8217;s badly overrated. Stephen Wolfram was also confused by this and &lt;a href="https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2015/12/untangling-the-tale-of-ada-lovelace/"&gt;decided to dig into it&lt;/a&gt;; he seems to rate her. I still think her story is more one of tragically wasted potential than actual lasting achievement, and we should maybe find some more women in computer science to name things after, but this and a couple of other things have definitely updated me regarding the depth and originality of her vision, and how great a tragedy her early death really was. (Content note: Stephen Wolfram&amp;#8217;s primary fascination is always Stephen Wolfram, so as always he mentions himself more often than you might naïvely think would be necessary, were you not aware of how great Stephen Wolfram&amp;nbsp;is.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, did you know that the &lt;a href="www.etymonline.com"&gt;Online Etymology Dictionary&lt;/a&gt; (one of my favourite websites) has a blog? It&amp;#8217;s true! And it&amp;#8217;s fascinating and grumpy and great. Highlights include my favourite ever discussion of &lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/columns/post/janus-words"&gt;autoantonyms&lt;/a&gt;, discussions of the knotty histories of &lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/columns/post/fast-company"&gt;&amp;#8220;fast&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/columns/post/of-guns-and-gunsels"&gt;&amp;#8220;gun&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, and lots of very entertaining ranting about how, no, your favourite word is &lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/columns/post/acronymphomania"&gt;not a fucking acronym&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolution is sampling error</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-12-12:/2019/12/12/evolution-is-sampling-error</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common mistake people make about evolution is to think it&amp;#8217;s all about natural selection and adaptation. In fact, random non-adaptive changes often dominate the evolutionary&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#8217;m going to lay out a useful framework that I hope makes this fact more intuitive, which might in turn …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common mistake people make about evolution is to think it&amp;#8217;s all about natural selection and adaptation. In fact, random non-adaptive changes often dominate the evolutionary&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#8217;m going to lay out a useful framework that I hope makes this fact more intuitive, which might in turn help non-experts build better intuitive models of evolutionary processes. This will come in handy when I try to explain non-adaptive theories of ageing later&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sampling error and genetic&amp;nbsp;drift&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think of evolution as &lt;em&gt;sampling error&lt;/em&gt;: deviation in the genetic composition of the offspring in a population relative to their parents. To illustrate this, let&amp;#8217;s imagine a simple, asexual population, evenly divided between two gene variants (alleles) which produce no difference in fitness&lt;sup id="fnref:assumptions"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:assumptions"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ten dots representing individuals, stacked vertically and coloured to represent their genotype: five red and five blue" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-0.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These individuals will reproduce, giving rise to the next generation. Since all the individuals are genetically identical and have the same chance of reproducing, we can think of these offspring being randomly sampled, with replacement, from the previous&amp;nbsp;generation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Two columns of ten dots, stacked vertically, with lines between the columns representing parentage. Some individuals produce no offspring, some one, and some more than one." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-1-keep.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there is a great deal of randomness involved in who reproduces successfully and whose offspring survive, not all individuals will produce the same number of offspring in the next generation, even though they all had the same probability of reproducing to begin with. As a result, even in the absence of selection effects, the allele distribution of the new generation is likely to differ from that of the previous generation; this random, unbiased change in allele distribution is known as &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_drift"&gt;genetic drift&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of genetic drift, the allele distribution will fluctuate up and down stochastically; sooner or later, one or the other will be eliminated from the population, resulting in &lt;em&gt;fixation&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Twenty columns of ten dots, stacked vertically, with lines between the columns representing parentage. The red allele reaches fixation at generation 14." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-mid-keep.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time to fixation depends on the population size&lt;sup id="fnref:effpop"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:effpop"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and some other population parameters; here&amp;#8217;s an example plot for a population with a carrying capacity of 200 instead of&amp;nbsp;10:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A plot of the allele frequency distribution of a larger population, reaching fixation at roughly generation 350." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-200-neutral-keep.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly dramatic genetic changes, then, can accumulate in a population based purely on genetic drift; there&amp;#8217;s not necessarily any need to invoke selection to explain why genetic differences between populations accumulate over time. That said, what happens when we add selection into the&amp;nbsp;mix?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Natural selection is sampling&amp;nbsp;bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose that one of the starting alleles in the population is less &lt;em&gt;fit&lt;/em&gt; than the other: individuals with that allele are less likely to produce reproductively-successful offspring. What happens&amp;nbsp;now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one allele is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less fit than the other, the individuals bearing it will probably die without issue, producing a very boring&amp;nbsp;plot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Another twenty-column plot, this time in green and purple. The single initial purple individual produces no offspring, so the purple lineage dies out immediately." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-vdel.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so trivial. The interesting cases occur when the fitness of one genotype is close to (either a bit higher or a bit lower than) the old one. In this case, thanks to genetic drift, the less-fit allele (here in purple) can persist in the population for a surprisingly long&amp;nbsp;time&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Another twenty-stage green-and-purple plot, this time representing two alleles with only a small difference in fitness. The less-fit purple allele persists until stage 18, then is lost." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-sdel-persist.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;or even&amp;nbsp;fix!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An independent run of the scenario from the previous figure. This time, the slightly-less-fit purple allele reaches fixation at stage 6." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-sdel-fixed.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, under these conditions (carrying capacity = 10, relative fitness ~ 0.9) the less-fit allele will reach fixation about a quarter of the time; more than enough for 100% the population to be bearing many deleterious&amp;nbsp;alleles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results are a pretty trivial application of statistics, but they have very important implications for how we should view evolution. Thanks to genetic drift, beneficial mutations will often die out and deleterious ones reach fixation. &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; often this occurs depends on various factors, the most obvious of which is the magnitude of the mutation&amp;#8217;s effect on fitness &amp;#8212; the more dramatic the effect, the greater selection&amp;#8217;s ability to overcome drift and eliminate the less-fit&amp;nbsp;allele.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, another crucial variable, underappreciated outside evolutionary biology, is population&amp;nbsp;size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Evolution and the law of large&amp;nbsp;numbers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_large_numbers"&gt;law of large numbers&lt;/a&gt;, the average of a sample converges in probability towards its expected value as sample size increases: the larger the sample, the smaller the expected relative mean absolute difference between the sample mean and the expected value&lt;sup id="fnref:rad"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:rad"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. If you flip a coin ten times, the chance of deviating from the expected value (five heads) by at least 20% is more than 75%, whereas it&amp;#8217;s only 5% if you flip 100 times and virtually zero if you flip 1000 times. The larger the sample, the more likely you are to see roughly what you&amp;nbsp;expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our framework of evolution as sampling error, natural selection determines the expected value: the number of offspring of each genotype we expect to see in the next generation, given the distribution in the current generation. But the smaller the population, the more likely it is to deviate substantially from this expectation – that is, for random genetic drift to overwhelm the bias imposed by natural&amp;nbsp;selection. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you combine this sample-size-dependent variability with the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Absorbing_states"&gt;absorbing&lt;/a&gt; nature of fixation and elimination (that is, once an allele has been eliminated, it isn&amp;#8217;t coming back), you obtain the result that &lt;strong&gt;the larger the population, the more likely it is that the fitter allele is actually the one that gets fixed&lt;/strong&gt;, all else equal. We can see this in our toy model from earlier, where the green allele is 10% fitter than the purple allele and both start with 50% prevalence in the&amp;nbsp;population:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A plot of population size vs probability of fixation for two competing alleles, one of which is 10% fitter than the other. The fitter allele fixes at just over 50% when population size is very small, rising to 100% at population sizes of 100 or larger." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-fix-even.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When population size is very small, the chance that the fitter (green) allele is the one that eventually fixes is close to 50%; as population size increases, this probability increases, until for sufficiently-large populations it is virtually certain. Smaller differences in fitness would require larger population sizes to consistently fix the fitter allele&lt;sup id="fnref:1percent"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1percent"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Population size, then, is a crucial factor affecting the optimisation power of evolution: the larger the population size, the greater the capacity of natural selection to select for beneficial mutations and eliminate deleterious ones. This is why &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Population_bottleneck"&gt;bottlenecks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founder_effect"&gt;founder effects&lt;/a&gt; are so important in evolution: by reducing the size of the population, they both increase the relative prevalence of rare mutations and decrease the relative strength of natural selection, resulting in very powerful drift. The results of this can be quite striking: on the tiny Micronesian island of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pingelap#Total_color_blindness"&gt;Pingelap&lt;/a&gt;, for example, almost 10% of the population are completely colourblind, a condition that is extremely rare elsewhere&lt;sup id="fnref:rare"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:rare"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This is believed to be the result of a typhoon in 1775 that left only 20 survivors, one of whom was a carrier of the condition&lt;sup id="fnref:carrier"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:carrier"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can we infer from all this? Firstly, when thinking about evolutionary processes it&amp;#8217;s vital not to neglect genetic drift. Just because something spread throughout a population and reached fixation does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean it is adaptive. Secondly, this is especially true when populations are small, and we should always pay careful attention to population size when thinking about how a population might evolve. In general, we should expect larger populations&lt;sup id="fnref:effpop2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:effpop2"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to be fitter than smaller ones, since (among other things) natural selection will be more effective at weeding out deleterious alleles and propagating beneficial&amp;nbsp;ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="http://www.lablit.com/article/11"&gt;it has not escaped my notice&lt;/a&gt; that this framework has obvious implications for thinking about analogous evolutionary processes that might occur outside of biology. More on this&amp;nbsp;anon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:assumptions"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m also assuming non-overlapping generations and a constant carrying capacity; relaxing these assumptions makes the maths more complicated but shouldn&amp;#8217;t alter the basic conclusion. Similarly, while new genetic variants are capable of spreading much more quickly through sexual populations, the same basic phenomena still apply.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:assumptions" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:effpop"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the time to fixation (and many other aspects of the population&amp;#8217;s behaviour) depend on its &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_population_size"&gt;effective population size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which depends not only on its actual population size but also on various demographic and genetic factors. This is an absolutely crucial distinction that I am eliding here for the sake of brevity (in my defence, population geneticists seem to also do the same thing when speaking casually). Effective population sizes are often much smaller than actual (&amp;#8220;census&amp;#8221;) sizes; for example, the usual estimate that gets bandied about for global human effective population size is roughly 10,000.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:effpop" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:rad"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RMD&lt;/span&gt; looks like it might vary as a power law of sample size:
&lt;img alt="A log-log plot of relative mean absolute difference vs sample size, showing a very linear-looking relationship" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/rmd-log-log.png"&gt;
I noticed this from simulations and haven&amp;#8217;t bothered to tease out the underlying mathematics here, but still, kinda cool.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:rad" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1percent"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See e.g. this plot for a 1% difference in fitness:
&lt;img alt="A plot of population size vs probability of fixation for two competing alleles, one of which is 1% fitter than the other. The fitter allele fixes at roughly 50% when population size is very small, rising to about 95% at a population size of 300. The rise in fixation rate is much slower than when the fitness difference was 10%." src="https://apomorphic.com/images/coalescent-fix-even-1percent.png"&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1percent" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:rare"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia, the proportion of Americans with the same condition is 0.003%.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:rare" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:carrier"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It probably didn&amp;#8217;t hurt that the suspected carrier was also the chief of the island.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:carrier" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:effpop2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;#8217;m actually talking about effective population size here, not census size.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:effpop2" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="evolution"></category><category term="statistics"></category></entry><entry><title>Linkpost 11/2019</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/11/03/linkpost-11-2019" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-11-03:/2019/11/03/linkpost-11-2019</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Stuff from&amp;nbsp;me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put up two more pieces on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum that I didn&amp;#8217;t think needed to be on this blog: a &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/3d2SbKC3bgXyEuExF/how-worried-should-i-be-about-a-childless-disneyland"&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; about Bostrom&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Disneyland without children&amp;#8221; and a &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/37T6NzajJ8j68x8DP/concrete-next-steps-for-ageing-based-welfare-measures"&gt;followup&lt;/a&gt; to my &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/27/ageing-biomarkers-welfare"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about ageing-based welfare measures with some concrete suggestions for future progress …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Stuff from&amp;nbsp;me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put up two more pieces on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum that I didn&amp;#8217;t think needed to be on this blog: a &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/3d2SbKC3bgXyEuExF/how-worried-should-i-be-about-a-childless-disneyland"&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; about Bostrom&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Disneyland without children&amp;#8221; and a &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/37T6NzajJ8j68x8DP/concrete-next-steps-for-ageing-based-welfare-measures"&gt;followup&lt;/a&gt; to my &lt;a href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/27/ageing-biomarkers-welfare"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about ageing-based welfare measures with some concrete suggestions for future progress in the&amp;nbsp;area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New&amp;nbsp;stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically, much of this stuff is not actually new, but I only came across it recently and &lt;em&gt;it&amp;#8217;s my blog&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lately I&amp;#8217;ve been enjoying Jason Crawford&amp;#8217;s blog &lt;a href="rootsofprogress.org"&gt;Roots of Progress&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;#8220;an intellectual project, which may take many years, to understand the nature and cause of human progress.&amp;#8221; Highlights include his &lt;a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/one-mans-junk"&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; of the fundamental artificiality of &amp;#8220;natural resources&amp;#8221; and his public boggling at the wonders of &lt;a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/iron-from-mythical-to-mundane"&gt;iron&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/instant-stone-just-add-water"&gt;cement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The classic story of how blind auditions reduced discrimination against women in orchestras &lt;a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2019/05/11/did-blind-orchestra-auditions-really-benefit-women/"&gt;may not be real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dutch have a special symbol called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flourish_of_approval"&gt;flourish of approval&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mole of moles &lt;a href="https://what-if.xkcd.com/4/"&gt;is a lot of moles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; is experimenting with new ways of &lt;a href="http://www.cidrap.umn.edu/news-perspective/2019/07/uk-test-new-payment-model-antibiotics"&gt;paying for antibiotics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Part of what makes us happy is the satisfaction of actually (or likely) helping people. &lt;a href="https://experiencemachines.wordpress.com/2018/06/10/demanding-gambles/"&gt;Consequentialism can ask us to give up even this&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s an actually-quite-old post about &lt;a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/11/1000000-grahams-number.html"&gt;Really Big Numbers&lt;/a&gt;. I still don&amp;#8217;t really comprehend Graham&amp;#8217;s Number, but at least I&amp;#8217;m starting to get an inkling of how unimaginably vast it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Golden&amp;nbsp;oldies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s some older stuff that I read a while ago, but has been on my mind for one reason or&amp;nbsp;another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading Roots of Progress reminds me of Kris De Decker&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="www.lowtechmagazine.com"&gt;Low Tech Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, a great example of what happens when you take widely-but-vaguely-held ideas seriously (in this case, a certain kind of environmental pessimism). His recent posts have mostly been less interesting to me, but he has a fantastic back catalogue of posts on obsolete technology: &lt;a href="https://www.lowtechmagazine.com/2010/01/wood-gas-cars.html"&gt;wood-powered cars&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.lowtechmagazine.com/2009/10/history-of-industrial-windmills.html"&gt;wind-powered factories&lt;/a&gt;, and even &lt;a href="https://www.lowtechmagazine.com/2013/09/power-from-the-tap-water-motors.html"&gt;fans and food mixers powered by tap water&lt;/a&gt;. And if you&amp;#8217;re unfamiliar with the technological marvel that is the Chinese wheelbarrow, don&amp;#8217;t miss his &lt;a href="https://www.lowtechmagazine.com/2011/12/the-chinese-wheelbarrow.html"&gt;magisterial summary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a similar vein, remember a few years ago when everyone got very excited about &lt;a href="http://nautil.us/issue/3/in-transit/the-box-that-built-the-modern-world"&gt;shipping containers&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, in case you haven&amp;#8217;t seen it before, here&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-N_RZJUAQY4"&gt;a two year old&amp;#8217;s solution to the trolley&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>Assessing biomarkers of ageing as measures of cumulative animal welfare</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/27/ageing-biomarkers-welfare" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-09-27:/2019/09/27/ageing-biomarkers-welfare</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is cross-posted from the Wild Animal Initiative website. The original is &lt;a href="https://www.wildanimalinitiative.org/blog/biomarkers-cumulative-welfare"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is also available on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/QnwxhgrFARoJ2sMvA/assessing-biomarkers-of-ageing-as-measures-of-cumulative"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to determine which conditions provide the best overall quality of life for nonhuman animals, it is important to be able to measure their cumulative …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is cross-posted from the Wild Animal Initiative website. The original is &lt;a href="https://www.wildanimalinitiative.org/blog/biomarkers-cumulative-welfare"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is also available on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EA&lt;/span&gt; Forum &lt;a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/QnwxhgrFARoJ2sMvA/assessing-biomarkers-of-ageing-as-measures-of-cumulative"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to determine which conditions provide the best overall quality of life for nonhuman animals, it is important to be able to measure their cumulative welfare experience. The ideal measure of cumulative welfare would be comprehensive, objectively measurable, and easy to transfer across species; however, existing approaches fall far short of this ideal. Recent academic work has suggested that measures of biological ageing could provide a highly promising alternative measure of cumulative welfare, which comes much closer to meeting these ideal&amp;nbsp;goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I review the existing empirical support for the use of biomarkers of ageing as a measure of cumulative welfare, discuss the prerequisites of applying the method, and explore a number of important caveats that may limit its applicability. Many of these caveats are particularly applicable to the study of wild-animal welfare, though some may also be important in domesticated&amp;nbsp;contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, despite some important potential weaknesses, biomarkers of ageing are likely to represent an important step forward in the assessment of cumulative animal welfare, which could potentially help resolve some important long-running uncertainties and disputes in the animal-welfare movement. Wild Animal Initiative recommends that both researchers and funders take note of these new techniques, and consider how best they can develop them further or apply them in their own domains of&amp;nbsp;expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;We need a good way of measuring cumulative animal&amp;nbsp;welfare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While single experiences can be acutely positive or negative, what matters more from a welfare perspective is the lasting cumulative impact of these&amp;nbsp;experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;— Bateson &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Pourier 2019&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref11:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of their life, an animal will undergo various positive and negative experiences. Some of these experiences will primarily affect welfare in an acute, short-lived manner, while others will have significant long-lasting welfare effects. The overall welfare state of an animal will be determined by the cumulative effect of all the experiences they have faced in the course of their life to&amp;nbsp;date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to improve animal welfare, we need to know what affects it. In order to improve animal welfare &lt;em&gt;effectively&lt;/em&gt;, we need to know which factors have the greatest total effect on animals’ cumulative wellbeing. Actually &lt;em&gt;measuring&lt;/em&gt; cumulative wellbeing, however, is highly challenging, and our existing methods for doing so frequently rely on crude proxies or error-prone anthropomorphic judgements. To make matters worse, the welfare effect of a given experience is frequently complex, species-specific, and non-obvious to&amp;nbsp;humans:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Species of fish which are naturally solitary exhibit stress indicators upon overcrowding, while schooling fish become stressed if raised at unnaturally low densities &lt;sup id="fnref2:ashley2007"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ashley2007"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exposure to environmental ultrasound frequencies that are undetectable to humans causes depression-like symptoms in laboratory rats and mice &lt;sup id="fnref:morozova2016"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:morozova2016"&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The flickering of some fluorescent lights at frequencies above the human &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flicker_fusion_threshold"&gt;flicker-fusion rate&lt;/a&gt; raises stress-hormone levels in starlings &lt;sup id="fnref:smith2005"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:smith2005"&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stress-hormone levels induced in captive-bred lizards by different experimental procedures can differ dramatically from how stressful human observers think the procedures are, with one controversial procedure found to generate much lower levels of stress hormone than the “less-stressful” procedure that replaced it &lt;sup id="fnref:langkilde2006"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:langkilde2006"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which specific stimuli are important for an animal&amp;#8217;s welfare is therefore very difficult to predict &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt;, and the use of anthropomorphism to make these predictions is fraught with&amp;nbsp;danger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it is possible to determine that a given experience is acutely positive or negative for an animal, it is not obvious how to convert these acute measurements into measurements of lasting impacts on welfare. Experiences with similar acute effects may have dramatically differences on long-run wellbeing: one stressor may involve temporary pain or result in a temporary spike in stress-hormone levels but have no long-term effects, while another might significantly contribute to long-term stress levels. In some cases, the short- and long-term welfare impacts of an exposure may even be of opposite sign: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hormesis"&gt;some acute stresses can be beneficial in the long-term&lt;/a&gt;, while the short-term pleasure of sugary food might be outweighed by the long-term pain caused by tooth decay and weight gain &lt;sup id="fnref:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Worse, the relationship between short-term and long-term welfare impacts is likely to vary significantly based on species, subspecies, chronological age, past experiences, and individual genetic variation, making the long-term welfare effect of an acute experience even more difficult to&amp;nbsp;predict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good measure of cumulative affective experience &lt;sup id="fnref:affect"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:affect"&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is therefore vital to the study of animal welfare. However, developing a cumulative-welfare metric which is sensitive, easy-to-measure, captures all or almost all of the relevant effects on welfare, and can be transferred with relative ease across species has proven to be highly challenging &lt;sup id="fnref2:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Existing measures include chronic physiological markers such as resting stress-hormone levels or bodyweight, acute behavioural measures such as the presence of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereotypy_(non-human)"&gt;stereotypies&lt;/a&gt;, and high-level behavioural measures such as depressive symptoms or cognitive biases &lt;sup id="fnref3:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; other measures combine multiple different sources of evidence, often alongside acute welfare indicators and/or subjective welfare assessments by a trained practitioner. However, all of these methods have serious drawbacks: physiological measures often lack sensitivity and specificity (i.e. they do not always reliably correlate with affective state), stereotypies are highly species-specific and often difficult to interpret, and the behavioural tests required to measure cognitive biases and mood must be developed and validated independently for each species and often require extensive animal training. Combined measures, meanwhile, rely on difficult-to-test assumptions about how different metrics should be combined and weighted to assess overall cumulative&amp;nbsp;wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ideal case, the many and varied inputs into cumulative animal welfare would be captured by a single, objectively measurable metric, which could then be used as a single readout of cumulative wellbeing for many different species of animals. In the rest of this article, I will review and discuss the evidence supporting a new, surprisingly good candidate for this “objectively measurable common currency” &lt;sup id="fnref4:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of wellbeing: biomarkers of the ageing&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biological ageing and cumulative animal&amp;nbsp;welfare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we get older, our bodies decay. In various ways, our cells and tissues progressively accumulate increasing levels of damage and dysregulation, leading at the whole-organism level to a decline in functionality, an increase in mortality, and a decrease in reproductive output &lt;sup id="fnref:hallmarks"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hallmarks"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. These deteriorative processes, which occur in broadly similar ways in many different animal species &lt;sup id="fnref:jones2014"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:jones2014"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, are collectively known as &lt;em&gt;ageing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among researchers studying the biology of ageing, it is well-known that simple chronological age is a less-than-perfect measure of the aspects of ageing we tend to care about. In humans, individuals of the same chronological age often differ substantially, both in how old they appear to others (degree of graying, wrinkles, stooping, etc.) and in their age-related health outcomes &lt;sup id="fnref:jia2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:jia2017"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It is therefore useful to separate the concepts of “chronological age” (time since conception or birth) and “biological age” (degree of age-related change/deterioration in appearance, health, or functionality) &lt;sup id="fnref2:jia2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:jia2017"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:horvath2018"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:horvath2018"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. So-called “biological ageing clocks”, which incorporate a variety of different types of biological data, are an active area of research in the study of human ageing, and the best such clocks can predict health and other outcomes much more accurately than chronological age alone &lt;sup id="fnref2:horvath2018"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:horvath2018"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biological age of an individual depends on their chronological age, genetic background, and environmental history: depending on their genes and experiences, two individuals of the same chronological age can differ substantially in their biological age. A striking example of this is smoking, which produces a variety of ageing-like symptoms and has recently been shown to substantially increase biological age in young humans &lt;sup id="fnref:smoking"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:smoking"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. However, biological age is affected by a wide variety of chemical, psychological and social stimuli, many of which are also known to have important effects on an individual&amp;#8217;s wellbeing. To take just one example, a wide variety of negative experiences (including anxiety, depression, childhood trauma, chronic pain, and various forms of stress) are associated with reduced &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telomere"&gt;telomere length&lt;/a&gt; in humans, while positive lifestyle factors are associated with longer telomeres &lt;sup id="fnref:bateson2016"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2016"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref5:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:pepper2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:pepper2019"&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:association"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:association"&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Despite important differences in telomere biology between species, a variety of stress manipulations (including social isolation, sleep disruption, injection of stress hormones, and crowding) have also been found to accelerate telomere attrition in various nonhuman animals, including wild and laboratory mice, chickens, starlings, and various other bird species &lt;sup id="fnref2:bateson2016"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2016"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this and other empirical data, there are good theoretical reasons to expect the rate of biological ageing to correlate with the cumulative affective experience of an individual &lt;sup id="fnref6:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Evolutionarily speaking, the affective state of an experience serves to motivate an animal to seek or avoid similar experiences; hence, affectively negative experiences tend to be those that reduce animal&amp;#8217;s fitness, while affectively positive experiences tend to be those that increase it. An important way in which an experience can decrease fitness is by causing or contributing to some sort of damage or dysregulation in the body; hence, experiences which contribute to damage or dysregulation will typically be perceived as aversive to the organism, while those that prevent or reverse damage (or have no effect on damage but are positive for some other reason) will be perceived as attractive. In general, therefore, there is good reason to expect physiologically-damaging experiences to be affectively negative, and vice versa &lt;sup id="fnref:stress"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:stress"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, with a similar connection between physiologically-protective experiences and positive affect. Since ageing is characterised by the progressive accumulation of various forms of physiological damage, this suggests that there is good reason to expect the affective valence (i.e. the positivity or negativity) of an experience to also generally correlate with its effect on biological&amp;nbsp;age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, therefore, both empirical data and theoretical arguments suggesting a relationship between cumulative affective experience and ageing. If this relationship exists, the biological age of an individual relative to their chronological age could be used to assess that individual’s cumulative welfare experience up to that point. If further testing bears this out, there are several reasons to expect biological age to be a particularly valuable tool for assessing&amp;nbsp;wellbeing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is highly &lt;strong&gt;general&lt;/strong&gt;, including all (or almost all) causes of stress and wellbeing experienced by the animal, including those not obvious or perceptible to&amp;nbsp;humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;strong&gt;cumulative&lt;/strong&gt;, giving a readout of the total affective history of an&amp;nbsp;individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is objectively &lt;strong&gt;measurable&lt;/strong&gt;, with well-established biomarkers already known for a number of&amp;nbsp;species&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, it is plausibly relatively &lt;strong&gt;phylogenetically neutral&lt;/strong&gt;: as ageing is a general phenomenon shared by very many species, whose measurement does not generally rely on anthropomorphic judgements, it can potentially be used to investigate welfare in many different animal&amp;nbsp;groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these potential advantages, how might we go about actually measuring biological&amp;nbsp;age?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Measuring biological age in non-human&amp;nbsp;animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any given species, the ageing process will manifest itself in a plethora of different phenotypes, many of which can be used to try to quantify biological ageing. In humans, a wide variety of biological readouts have been used as biomarkers of ageing, including telomere length and attrition rate, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNA&lt;/span&gt; methylation patterns, gene expression profiles, changes in neuroanatomy, proteomic and metabolomic changes, and various composites of clinically relevant symptoms &lt;sup id="fnref7:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:belsky2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:belsky2017"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:cole2018"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:cole2018"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. While many of these biomarkers predict health outcomes better than chronological age, they often reflect different aspects of the ageing process and do not always correlate well with one another &lt;sup id="fnref8:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref2:belsky2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:belsky2017"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Combining different measures (e.g. with machine-learning-based prediction tools) can overcome these problems and improve the ability of a biological ageing measure to predict health outcomes &lt;sup id="fnref2:cole2018"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:cole2018"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref2:smoking"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:smoking"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As different biomarkers of ageing track different aspects of the ageing process, they may differ in how well they measure cumulative subjective wellbeing.  A good biomarker of cumulative experience should provide a single, continuous, easy-to-measure readout that responds in opposite directions to positive and negative affective experiences in a cumulative and dose-dependent manner &lt;sup id="fnref3:bateson2016"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2016"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref9:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Different biomarkers will also differ in the money, expertise and time required to obtain good measurements, and in the ease with which they can be validated in a new context. As nonhuman animals, unlike humans, cannot explicitly self-report their subjective experience, validation of a new potential biomarker&amp;#8217;s relationship with  wellbeing is much more challenging in these species; as a result, the ease and reliability with which a biomarker can be transferred between species is an additional important consideration when choosing how to measure biological age in an animal-welfare&amp;nbsp;context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I would expect more complex and multi-modal measures to provide a more accurate, precise and thorough measure of biological age and so give a better idea of an animal&amp;#8217;s cumulative experience. On the other hand, I would expect these complex measures to be more expensive and time-consuming to obtain for each individual, and less transferable between&amp;nbsp;species. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some widely-used farmed species and experimental model organisms, it may well be worth developing sophisticated species-specific methods of measuring biological age and hence cumulative welfare; however, in contexts where resources are highly limited and/or the number of species of concern is large, cost and transferability concerns are likely to mitigate in favour of simpler, faster, cruder measures &lt;sup id="fnref:complex"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:complex"&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Bateson &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Pourier &lt;sup id="fnref4:bateson2016"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2016"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref10:bateson2019"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; suggest telomere length and hippocampal volume as two metrics that are simple, well-defined, and likely to retain validity across a wide variety of vertebrate species; further work may reveal other promising candidates. However, when using such very simple readouts of biological age, it is important to remember that they may give a significantly more partial and inaccurate reading than more sophisticated measures, and to seek to develop such improved measures where&amp;nbsp;feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A concrete example: the welfare effect of crowding on farmed&amp;nbsp;fishes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many farmed fish are kept at very high densities, in a manner which often appears to be detrimental to their welfare &lt;sup id="fnref:ashley2007"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ashley2007"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The potential welfare effects of crowding are many and varied, including social stresses, reduced water quality, and increased disease transmission. However, the actual welfare effect of a given level of crowding will vary between fish populations, depending on the level of crowding and water quality they are adapted to cope with, the robustness of their immune systems, and whether they have been vaccinated, among other factors. It would be useful to measure the total cumulative welfare effect of different crowding regimes on different species, and to know the degree to which other interventions such as vaccination mitigate any crowding-induced welfare reduction. Biological age provides an ideal means of addressing these&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply this method, we would need some sort of biological ageing clock for each of the fish species of interest, as well as some way of keeping track of the chronological age of each individual. Once these two methods are in place for each species, the experiment is simple: simply raise populations of fish at different levels of crowding, sample the biological ages of individuals in each population, then compare the biological ages of chronological-age-matched individuals from different conditions. Those populations exhibiting the highest biological age relative to their chronological age would be taken as experiencing the lowest levels of cumulative&amp;nbsp;welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Three speculative line graphs, each with three lines, indicating the rate of biological age accumulation for fish under low-, medium- and high-density conditions in a hypothetical experiment. The leftmost plot shows hypothetical results for schooling fish and shows slowest accumulation in the mid-density condition, indicating a preference for moderate density for those fish. The middle plot shows results for solitary fish and shows the rate of accumulation increasing progressively with density, showing that these fish are negatively affected by any level of population density above the minimum. Finally, the rightmost plot shows results for solitary fish with vaccination, indicating that vaccination improves welfare at all density levels with an especially strong effect at higher densities. All results are speculative." src="https://i.imgur.com/1qUUyhv.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plots showing speculative results of a hypothetical experiment investigating the effect of crowding on fish welfare, indicating that biological age accumulates slowest (indicating highest welfare) at low densities for solitary fish and middling densities for schooling fish, with a positive welfare effect of vaccination. The shape of the curves is&amp;nbsp;arbitrary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make up some totally speculative results, these biological ageing data might indicate that naturally solitary fish exhibit significant welfare declines from any level of crowding, while schooling fish have a preferred crowding level and experience reduced welfare above or below this level. These welfare declines may or may not be abrogated by interventions such as vaccination, better water filtration, or changes in feeding schedule. By collapsing all (or most) of an animal&amp;#8217;s welfare experience into a single, objective, cumulative measure, many different experiments of this kind could be performed quickly and efficiently, providing a more comprehensive picture of the welfare effects of crowding on fish&amp;nbsp;wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the idea that crowding is bad for fish welfare may not be particularly controversial, this approach would allow researchers to empirically quantify how bad that effect is compared to other aspects of a farmed fish&amp;#8217;s life, and assess the efficacy of different interventions (such as vaccination or water oxygenation) for mitigating that welfare impact. The same technique could be applied to help resolve active empirical controversies in the animal welfare movement, such as the &lt;a href="https://www.openphilanthropy.org/blog/new-report-welfare-differences-between-cage-and-cage-free-housing"&gt;relative welfare levels of caged vs cage-free chickens&lt;/a&gt;, the relative importance of &lt;a href="http://www.charityentrepreneurship.com/blog/helping-fish-breathe-a-promising-intervention-for-animals"&gt;water oxygenation&lt;/a&gt; in the welfare of farmed fishes, or the net welfare impact of &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/how-bringing-back-predators-can-change-the-way-prey-behaves-56216"&gt;predator reintroduction&lt;/a&gt; on prey&amp;nbsp;species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Limitations and&amp;nbsp;caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was initially sceptical about the applicability of biological ageing markers as measures of animal welfare, I have generally been convinced that this represents a novel and important advance in the field. Nevertheless, there are a number of important limitations or difficulties I anticipate in actually applying the method, which I think it is important to be aware of and mitigate where possible. I have divided these limitations into two categories: contexts where the prerequisites of applying the method may be difficult or expensive to obtain, and contexts where the link between ageing and welfare may be weakened or broken&amp;nbsp;entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Difficulties in&amp;nbsp;application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The need for biological ageing&amp;nbsp;clocks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use biological ageing as a cumulative welfare measure in a given species, we need some kind of biological ageing measure for that species. As discussed above, these range in complexity from simple metrics like telomere length to highly complex machine-learning-based predictors, and there is likely to be a tradeoff between the accuracy and comprehensiveness of a measure on the one hand and its affordability and transferability on the other. As funding is very limited in many animal-welfare contexts, it is likely that simpler, cheaper metrics that can be transferred between species with relatively little validation will be preferred; however, it is important to remember that these may only provide a partial measure of biological&amp;nbsp;age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best biomarkers of ageing to use for these experiments will depend on the species being tested and its relationship to other well-validated model systems. In many vertebrate species, and probably most mammals, the markers established in humans and laboratory mice are likely to be the best option. Conversely, in species very distantly related to humans the validity of these markers may be limited: insects, for example, are largely post-mitotic in their adult form (limiting the usefulness of telomere attrition as a biomarker) and have very different neuroanatomy from vertebrates (preventing the use of hippocampal volume). If it is desirable to apply these ageing-based methods to assess welfare in these species, alternative biomarkers (such as accumulation of fluorescent advanced glycation end products in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:jacobson2010"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:jacobson2010"&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) will need to be developed and validated as welfare measures, substantially increasing the upfront&amp;nbsp;cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Experimental&amp;nbsp;controls&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While biological ageing is a promising measure of cumulative welfare, it is important to remember that welfare is not the only thing affecting biological age. Most obviously, chronological age has a very strong effect on biological age, and studies should always compare age-matched individuals when possible. Genetic variability is also an important factor: many species exhibit substantially different lifespans in different populations, and polymorphisms within a population can also have a substantial effect. As a result, ageing-based welfare measures will be most reliable in contexts where all individuals are genetically homogeneous, or at least where there is no systematic difference in genetic composition between different experimental groups. Finally, there should of course be as little systematic difference in environment as possible between the groups being compared, other than whatever exposure is being investigated for its welfare&amp;nbsp;effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these control requirements, the need for genetic comparability between experimental groups is the most frustrating, as it appears to exclude a lot of factors that are widely thought to be important for animal welfare, particularly in domesticated contexts where animals&amp;#8217; genotypes have been &lt;a href="https://www.onegreenplanet.org/animalsandnature/the-genetically-modified-chicken-how-we-have-altered-broiler-chickens-for-profit/"&gt;substantially modified by humans&lt;/a&gt; through selective breeding. On the face of it, biological-ageing methods seem to be unable to address this, as the groups being compared are not genetically comparable. However, given the importance of genetic effects on welfare in many contexts, any way to overcome this limitation would be very useful, and further investigation on this front seems quite valuable in&amp;nbsp;expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Limitations to&amp;nbsp;validity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Death and other acute&amp;nbsp;events&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, a large portion of the suffering experienced by an animal, whether domesticated or wild, is suspected to take place acutely at the moment of death. If this death is sufficiently gruesome, the suffering so engendered could potentially outweigh the entire net welfare of a life that is otherwise worth living. Despite its importance, however, it seems unlikely that the suffering entailed by dying would be adequately reflected in ageing-based measures of cumulative welfare. For one thing, there would be no opportunity for the negative experiences associated with the animal’s death to be reflected as a subsequent increase in the rate of biological ageing; for another, the extensive physiological damage resulting from death would prevent an accurate postmortem assessment of biological age in many cases. Hence, an important limitation of ageing-based methods of measuring welfare may be their inability to incorporate the affective experience of&amp;nbsp;dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar concern might apply, albeit to a much lesser extent, to other highly acute exposures, i.e. those with large but short-lived effects on welfare. Many of these will be reflected in ongoing cumulative welfare to some extent (e.g. as physical or psychological trauma in the case of negative events), but it’s not clear to me that the cumulative readout of welfare given by ageing biomarkers will always incorporate them adequately. More research may be needed&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Differences between juveniles and&amp;nbsp;adults&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both wild and domesticated contexts, many of the animals of greatest concern from a welfare perspective are juveniles who have not yet reached reproductive maturation. These immature individuals are often much more numerous than adults, and have less chance to accumulate positive experiences to outweigh the pain of&amp;nbsp;dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For animals that die shortly after birth or hatching, the cumulative welfare of their lives is likely to be dominated by the affective experience of dying, and this experience will not be adequately reflected in biological ageing markers. Ageing-based approaches therefore seem unable to effectively address the welfare of these individuals; on the other hand, it seems likely that any measure of cumulative welfare will run into the same&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation for individuals that have relatively long lives as juveniles is more complex. In many species, juvenile and adult individuals differ substantially in their biology, and the question of whether juveniles are &amp;#8220;ageing&amp;#8221; is somewhat fraught. There are certainly dramatic changes taking place over the course of development, some of which could be interpreted as an accumulation of damage: telomeres, for example, shorten rapidly during the period of juvenile growth &lt;sup id="fnref:zeichner1999"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:zeichner1999"&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. On the other hand, many clinical biomarkers of ageing do not begin to accumulate until adulthood &lt;sup id="fnref:hollingsworth1965"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hollingsworth1965"&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This means that the applicability of biological-ageing measures to juveniles depends on the specific biomarkers being used, and different markers are likely to be most appropriate for measuring juvenile vs adult wellbeing &lt;sup id="fnref:juveniles"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:juveniles"&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Animals very different from&amp;nbsp;humans&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence supporting the use of biological ageing markers as measures of cumulative welfare falls into three broad categories: a theoretical, evolutionary argument linking the affective status of an exposure to its effect on ageing via its effect on somatic damage; extensive empirical research in humans associating biological ageing markers with directly reported affective mood (e.g. stress, depression or anxiety) and experiences known to impact mood (e.g. trauma, pain, exercise, and sleep); and more limited empirical research in animals linking these markers to experiences that are both plausibly affectively relevant and associated with other widely-used welfare&amp;nbsp;measures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second of these, empirical data on humans, is particularly important, as only humans are capable of directly reporting their affective state to human researchers and so directly confirming a link between biological ageing and welfare. As one moves away from humans in terms of the species under investigation, the less weight can be put on this source of evidence in support of this link, and the more one has to rely on the first and third sources of evidence outlined above. The more distant and dissimilar a species is from those species in which ageing-base techniques have been empirically studied, the more our confidence in those techniques should decrease towards the level of confidence we have in the theoretical argument alone. This poses an issue, since the vast majority of animals on the planet fall into this&amp;nbsp;category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two particular groups of animals for which I think the existing empirical data provides relatively little support for ageing-based welfare measures: invertebrates, and those animals (both vertebrate and invertebrate) whose pattern of lifetime ageing differs substantially from that of humans. The reasons for scepticism in the first case are clear: invertebrates are very different from vertebrates in many aspects of their biology, differ substantially from mammals in terms of their biomarkers of ageing (see above), are very diverse amongst themselves, and are almost totally unstudied as objects of welfare concern. My concerns about the second group, however, are likely to be less clear to someone outside the ageing field, and I will try to briefly explain my reasons&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, under simple assumptions that are frequently roughly met in real animals, we expect to see mortality progressively increase and fecundity progressively decrease with time after reproductive maturation &lt;sup id="fnref:charlesworth2000"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:charlesworth2000"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Many animals, including humans and nearly all common domesticated species, follow this pattern, but this does not apply universally to all animals. Some species, most famously the green hydra &lt;sup id="fnref:danko2015"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:danko2015"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and more recently the naked mole rat &lt;sup id="fnref:ruby2018"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ruby2018"&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, do not appear to age at all, while some (including various corals, reptiles and amphibians &lt;sup id="fnref2:jones2014"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:jones2014"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) seem to &amp;#8220;age in reverse&amp;#8221;, exhibiting &lt;em&gt;declining&lt;/em&gt; mortality with age until&amp;nbsp;death. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These differences in life history could pose major problems for the use of biological ageing markers as a measure of cumulative welfare in these species. To begin with, it isn’t clear how to define the concept of biological age, let alone measure it, in an animal that does not age in any conventional way. Some subset of conventional biomarkers of ageing may still accumulate with time in these species, but that subset is likely to differ from taxon to taxon depending on what biological methods they have used to overcome the ageing process. Worse, even the theoretical argument in support of ageing-based welfare measures in these species may be greatly weakened: for an animal to exhibit no ageing or even reverse ageing over a prolonged time period, they must be either extremely resistant to somatic damage or have extremely good mechanisms in place to repair that damage, meaning the relationship between damaging (and therefore aversive) experiences and ageing may be largely or entirely&amp;nbsp;severed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues will pose little difficulty to researchers and activists concerned with the welfare of agricultural, experimental or other captive animals, most or all of which, to my knowledge, follow the conventional pattern of ageing exhibited by humans, mice and &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;. However, they could turn out to be significant for researchers interested in quantifying and improving the welfare of wild animals, who will inevitably have to tackle the welfare of large numbers of animals very different from humans. The extent to which these &amp;#8220;unconventional&amp;#8221; life histories are widespread in the natural world is unclear to me at present, and could be an important factor affecting the applicability of these methods in certain&amp;nbsp;contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding better methods with which to quantitatively measure the cumulative welfare experience of nonhuman animals would represent a major advance in the study of animal welfare. As a potential route to a better and more objective measure of cumulative welfare, biomarkers of ageing are potentially very&amp;nbsp;promising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the caveats I outlined above are educated guesses and may well turn out to be circumventable with sufficient thought and care. If they are not, how serious a problem would this pose for the practical usefulness of this method? In the case of domesticated animals, an inability to compare groups differing systematically in their genetics or adequately incorporate the badness of death are all significant limitations, but would still leave us with a tool which could be gainfully applied in many important contexts. For wild animals, the issues are more serious: there are vastly more species for which we would have to develop methods of measuring biological age, it is much harder to perform well-controlled longitudinal experiments, and many more of the animals of concern fall into categories for which I am more sceptical about the theoretical applicability of the method. A further concern is that measuring chronological age accurately is often difficult for wild animals, potentially undermining one of the foundations of ageing-based welfare measures. Nevertheless, of all the methods we might think of for measuring the cumulative welfare of wild animals, biomarkers of ageing seem to be among the least hopeless, and among those most worth developing further in the hopes of overcoming some of these pervasive&amp;nbsp;issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am currently very optimistic about the value of applying these methods in domesticated contexts, and cautiously optimistic about applying them to wild ecosystems. I would recommend that researchers interested in the welfare of either domesticated or wild animals take note of these techniques and consider their applicability in their own domains, and that funders in this space seriously consider funding their further development and application to new contexts. On a meta level, I think the surprisingly strong applicability of techniques from the biology of ageing to animal welfare science should encourage us all to look for innovative, unexpected and interdisciplinary ways to help nonhuman animals: as is often the case in science, the crucial insights and discoveries may not be at all where we expect them to&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report was funded by the Wild Animal Initiative, and many &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAI&lt;/span&gt; researchers (including Luke Hecht, Michelle Graham, Hollis Howe and Jane Capozzelli) contributed their time to reviewing and suggesting improvements to the draft. Prof. Melissa Bateson, the author of the key sources for the report, also generously read the draft and provided crucial&amp;nbsp;feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bateson2019"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bateson, M., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Poirier, C. (2019). Can biomarkers of biological age be used to assess cumulative lifetime experience? &lt;em&gt;Anim. Welf.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;28&lt;/strong&gt;: 41-56.  doi: 10.7120/09627286.28.1.041&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref4:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref5:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref6:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref7:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref8:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref9:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref10:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref11:bateson2019" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:medawar1952"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medawar, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;P. B.&lt;/span&gt;(1952). An unsolved problem of biology. London: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HK&lt;/span&gt; Lewis &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Co&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:medawar1952" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:stress"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major category of negative experiences which do not appear to be directly damaging (but are nevertheless important to an animal&amp;#8217;s wellbeing) are social experiences. For many reasons, an animal&amp;#8217;s social status and relationships are very important to their survival and reproduction, but are not typically the direct cause of bodily damage. However, negative social experiences (low status, rejection by mates, ostracism) do give rise to significant levels of stress in many species, and this stress is well known to be physiologically damaging.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:stress" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bateson2016"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bateson, M. (2016). Cumulative stress in research animals: Telomere attrition as a biomarker in a welfare context?. &lt;em&gt;BioEssays&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;38&lt;/strong&gt; (2): 201-212.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bateson2016" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:bateson2016" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:bateson2016" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref4:bateson2016" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:belsky2017"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belsky, D. W., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2017). Eleven telomere, epigenetic clock, and biomarker-composite quantifications of biological aging: do they measure the same thing? &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;187&lt;/strong&gt; (6): 1220-1230.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:belsky2017" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:belsky2017" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:cole2018"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cole, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;J. H.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2018). Brain age predicts mortality. &lt;em&gt;Molecular Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;23&lt;/strong&gt; (5): 1385-1392.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:cole2018" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:cole2018" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ashley2007"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashley, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;P. J.&lt;/span&gt;(2007). Fish welfare: current issues in aquaculture. &lt;em&gt;Applied Animal Behaviour Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;104&lt;/strong&gt; (3-4): 199-235.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ashley2007" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:ashley2007" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hallmarks"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;López-Otín, C., Blasco, M. A., Partridge, L., Serrano, M., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Kroemer, G. (2013). The Hallmarks of Aging. &lt;em&gt;Cell&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;153&lt;/strong&gt; (6): 1194-1217.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hallmarks" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:jones2014"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jones, O. R., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2014). Diversity of ageing across the tree of life. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;505&lt;/strong&gt; (7482): 169.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:jones2014" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:jones2014" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:jia2017"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jia, L., Zhang, W., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Chen, X. (2017). Common methods of biological age estimation. &lt;em&gt;Clinical Interventions in Aging&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt;: 759-772.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:jia2017" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:jia2017" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:horvath2018"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horvath, S., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Raj, K. (2018). &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNA&lt;/span&gt; methylation-based biomarkers and the epigenetic clock theory of ageing. &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Genetics&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;19&lt;/strong&gt; (6): 371-384.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:horvath2018" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:horvath2018" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:smoking"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mamoshina, P., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2019). Blood Biochemistry Analysis to Detect Smoking Status and Quantify Accelerated Aging in Smokers. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt;: 142.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:smoking" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:smoking" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:langkilde2006"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Langkilde, T., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Shine, R. (2006). How much stress do researchers inflict on their study animals? A case study using a scincid lizard, &lt;em&gt;Eulamprus heatwolei&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;209&lt;/strong&gt; (6): 1035-1043.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:langkilde2006" title="Jump back to footnote 13 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:danko2015"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dańko, M. J., Kozłowski, J., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Schaible, R. (2015). Unraveling the non-senescence phenomenon in &lt;em&gt;Hydra&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Theoretical Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;382&lt;/strong&gt;: 137-149.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:danko2015" title="Jump back to footnote 14 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ruby2018"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruby, J. G., Smith, M., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Buffenstein, R. (2018). Naked mole-rat mortality rates defy Gompertzian laws by not increasing with age. &lt;em&gt;eLife&lt;/em&gt; 7:e31157.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ruby2018" title="Jump back to footnote 15 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:charlesworth2000"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlesworth, B. (2000). Fisher, Medawar, Hamilton and the evolution of aging. &lt;em&gt;Genetics&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;156&lt;/strong&gt; (3): 927-931.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:charlesworth2000" title="Jump back to footnote 16 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:williams1957"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Williams, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;G. C.&lt;/span&gt;(1957). Pleiotropy, natural selection, and the evolution of senescence. &lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;(4): 398-411.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:williams1957" title="Jump back to footnote 17 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:zeichner1999"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zeichner, S. L., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (1999). Rapid telomere shortening in children. &lt;em&gt;Blood&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;93&lt;/strong&gt; (9): 2824-2830.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:zeichner1999" title="Jump back to footnote 18 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hollingsworth1965"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hollingsworth, J. W., Hashizume, A., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Jablon, S. (1965). Correlations between tests of aging in Hiroshima subjects—an attempt to define &amp;#8220;physiologic age&amp;#8221;. &lt;em&gt;Yale J Biol Med&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;38&lt;/strong&gt; (1): 11-26.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hollingsworth1965" title="Jump back to footnote 19 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:jacobson2010"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacobson, J., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2010). Biomarkers of aging in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Aging Cell&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; (4): 466-477.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:jacobson2010" title="Jump back to footnote 20 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:morozova2016"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morozova, A., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2016) Ultrasound of alternating frequencies and variable emotional impact evokes depressive syndrome in mice and rats. &lt;em&gt;Progress in Neuropsychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;68&lt;/strong&gt;: 52-63.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:morozova2016" title="Jump back to footnote 21 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:smith2005"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, E.L., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2005) Effect of repetitive visual stimuli on behaviour and plasma corticosterone of European starlings. &lt;em&gt;Animal Biology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;55&lt;/strong&gt;: 245-258.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:smith2005" title="Jump back to footnote 22 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:affect"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this piece I am assuming that welfare is synonymous with affect, i.e. with subjectively positive and negative experiences. This is not an uncontroversial position, and there are many in the animal-welfare field who prefer a concept of welfare which incorporates both affective wellbeing and physical health, or even avoids questions of subjective experience altogether &lt;sup id="fnref:dawkins2017"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:dawkins2017"&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. While I&amp;#8217;m sceptical about this, it&amp;#8217;s worth noting that measures of cumulative wellbeing are also essential when using such a definition, so it doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily change many of the conclusions of this report.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:affect" title="Jump back to footnote 23 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:dawkins2017"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dawkins, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;M. S.&lt;/span&gt;(2017) Animal welfare with and without consciousness. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Zoology&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;301&lt;/strong&gt;: 1-10.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:dawkins2017" title="Jump back to footnote 24 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:pepper2019"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pepper, G.V., &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2018) Telomeres as integrative markers of exposure to stress and aversity: a systematic review and meta-analysis. &lt;em&gt;Royal Society Open Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;: 180744.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:pepper2019" title="Jump back to footnote 25 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:association"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s important to stress here that the great majority of research into the association between lifestyle and telomere length is cross-sectional and correlational: individuals with greater exposure to adversity have shorter telomeres. This finding is robust, but not causal: it doesn&amp;#8217;t demonstrate that these adverse experiences cause shorter telomeres. Evidence from longitudinal studies, for example on smoking &lt;sup id="fnref:bateson2019b"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bateson2019b"&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, tend to find a much smaller effect; more on this later.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:association" title="Jump back to footnote 26 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bateson2019b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bateson, M. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2019). Smoking does not accelerate leucocyte telomere attrition: a meta-analysis of 18 longitudinal cohorts. &lt;em&gt;Royal Society Open Science&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;: 190420.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bateson2019b" title="Jump back to footnote 27 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:complex"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melissa Bateson (pers. comm.) points out that a &amp;#8220;complex and multi-modal&amp;#8221; measure of biological ageing does not necessarily entail expensive and expertise-heavy multi-omics methods. An alternative approach, which captures the goal of assessing many different aspects of an animal&amp;#8217;s biology while being much cheaper, is a &amp;#8220;biomarker panel&amp;#8221; approach, in which a large number of different easy-to-measure features that are associated with poor health in old age are collected from the same individuals. These could then be used as input to a machine-learning model which has been trained to use them to predict biological age. This approach has many advantages, including potentially high reliability and low cost. However, it seems to require a fairly high level of interaction with the animal (at least in humans and lab animals, many of the markers used are often behavioural), making it difficult to use in wild contexts, and is probably quite species-specific. Both of these issues could be overcome to some extent through the choice of biomarkers used.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:complex" title="Jump back to footnote 28 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:juveniles"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of telomere attrition, juveniles may actually be more appropriate subjects than adults (M. Bateson, pers. comm.): the base rate of telomere attrition is much higher, which makes changes in the attrition rate due to welfare factors easier to detect. It is also much easier, quicker and cheaper to do longitudinal studies on juveniles, avoiding many of the interpretation issues associated with cross-sectional studies.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:juveniles" title="Jump back to footnote 29 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="ageing"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="animal welfare"></category><category term="effective altruism"></category></entry><entry><title>Why We Age, Part 1: What ageing is and is not</title><link href="https://apomorphic.com/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Will Bradshaw</name></author><id>tag:apomorphic.com,2019-09-09:/2019/09/09/why-we-age-1-intro</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the LessWrong European Community Weekend 2018, I gave a talk explaining the intuition behind non-adaptive theories of the evolution of ageing. This blog post and its followup are adapted from that&amp;nbsp;presentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people find out that I did my PhD in the biology of ageing, they tend to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the LessWrong European Community Weekend 2018, I gave a talk explaining the intuition behind non-adaptive theories of the evolution of ageing. This blog post and its followup are adapted from that&amp;nbsp;presentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people find out that I did my PhD in the biology of ageing, they tend to ask one of two questions. First, they ask what they can do to live longer. Second, they ask why people age in the first place. My answer to the first question is unfortunately fairly boring at present &amp;#8212; don&amp;#8217;t smoke, eat well, get enough exercise, get enough sleep, &lt;em&gt;et cetera&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; but when it comes to the second I think I have more of interest to say. To get this blog rolling (see what I did there), let&amp;#8217;s dive into the important and fractious question of why we&amp;nbsp;age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is&amp;nbsp;ageing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a curious thing that there is no word in the English language that stands for the mere increase of years; that is, for ageing without its connotations of increasing deterioration and&amp;nbsp;decay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;—Peter Medawar, &amp;#8220;An Unsolved Problem in&amp;nbsp;Biology&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people talk about &amp;#8220;ageing&amp;#8221;, there are broadly speaking three different things they might mean&lt;sup id="fnref:popage"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:popage"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Firstly, there is the simple process of getting older &amp;#8212; of the amount of time since you were born inexorably increasing. Let&amp;#8217;s call this process &amp;#8220;temporal ageing&amp;#8221;. Ageing in this way has a lot of benefits: more memories, more experience, and with luck more self-knowledge and more&amp;nbsp;wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the benefits conferred by temporal ageing are currently inextricably tied to the physical changes denoted by the second meaning of &amp;#8220;ageing&amp;#8221;: a generalised physiological deterioration, characterised by a wide range of unfortunate symptoms affecting almost every system of the body. As a result of this second kind of ageing, we become slower, more fragile, more prone to disease, and generally more likely to experience impaired health and wellbeing as we get older, eventually leading to death. As we as a civilisation have gradually eliminated more and more extrinsic forms of suffering and death, the depredations of ageing have gradually become the primary cause of ill health and death in developed countries by an overwhelming margin. This is the kind of ageing people mean when they worry about getting cancer or dementia, buy &amp;#8220;anti-ageing&amp;#8221; skin cream, or invest in real anti-ageing research; it&amp;#8217;s the province of doctors, physiologists, and molecular biologists. Let&amp;#8217;s call it &amp;#8220;physiological&amp;nbsp;ageing&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the individual changes taking place due to physiological ageing give rise to a distinctive statistical pattern at the level of entire populations of humans or other animals: a progressive increase in mortality (probability of dying) and decrease in fecundity (expected number of offspring) in older age cohorts. This pattern is what gives rise to plots like the ones below, and it&amp;#8217;s what demographers, actuaries and evolutionary biologists generally mean when they talk about &amp;#8220;ageing&amp;#8221;. From this perspective, the specific functional changes underlying these changes in survival and reproduction are less important than the high-level functional changes that result: changes in the rates of reproduction, illness, disability, and death. From an evolutionary perspective it is the first and last of these, reproduction and death rates, that are the most important. We can call this final meaning of the word ageing &amp;#8220;demographic&amp;nbsp;ageing&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/gompertz.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Logarithmic mortality curves for British and American populations at different points in the 20th century. The &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt;-axes give the log-probability of dying for individuals in a given age-class in the year and country indicated. Source: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; Office of Retirement and Disability&amp;nbsp;Policy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two phenomena, of physiological and demographic ageing, are tightly interlinked in any given population but are nevertheless conceptually distinct: two different species (an insect and a mammal, say) could undergo very different physiological ageing processes but exhibit very similar patterns of demographic ageing. Physiological and demographic ageing also give us very different perspectives on the question of why we age. From the perspective of physiological ageing, the question is generally asking about the specific genetic, molecular, histological or physiological mechanisms underlying the changes we observe: what particular aspect of our biology is causing our bodies to deteriorate with age in this or that particular way? From the perspective of demographic ageing, the relevant &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; question is simpler and more fundamental: given that ageing appears to be pretty deleterious to the survival and reproduction chances of any individual experiencing it, how could we have evolved to exhibit declining functionality with age &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these posts, I&amp;#8217;ll be focusing on the second kind of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; question, discussing the evolutionary teleology of the ageing process. As we&amp;#8217;ll see, from that perspective, ageing is frankly pretty&amp;nbsp;weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Three puzzles of&amp;nbsp;ageing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we look at nature, or at ourselves, we observe something surprising: animals get old. In many, many different species, old age is accompanied by a progressive decline in functionality, leading to higher rates of death&lt;sup id="fnref:mortality"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:mortality"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and lower rates of reproduction. This pattern is seen almost everywhere you look in the animal kingdom, suggesting that it has either evolved again and again independently or been retained after inheritance from a common ancestor. Yet despite this commonality, there is profound variation in the details of the ageing process: even closely related species can differ dramatically in how quickly they age and how long they tend to live. And here and there, we see species that seem to have escaped the iron grip of ageing, exhibiting mortality that stays constant or even declines over&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="https://apomorphic.com/images/bats_mice.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distribution of lifespans across all mouse and bat species from the AnAge database (accessed 2018-09-01). Despite their relatively close relationship, similar size, and similar metabolic rates, bats live dramatically longer than&amp;nbsp;mice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, then, is the threefold puzzle of ageing. Why should a process that appears to be so deleterious to the individuals experiencing it have evolved to be so widespread in nature? Given this ubiquity, which implies there is some compelling evolutionary reason for ageing to exist, why do different animals vary so much in their lifespans? And how, when ageing has either evolved or been retained in so many different lineages, have some animals evolved to escape&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any successful theory of the evolution of ageing must be able to convincingly answer all these questions. A number of attempts have been made over the years, none of which has managed to capture the consensus of the academic community. These attempted explanations can be broadly divided into two groups: those that propose with some reason why ageing, which seems so deleterious, is adaptive after all, and those that accept that ageing is deleterious and attempt to explain why it might evolve anyway. I&amp;#8217;ll discuss the main representatives of each group in separate blog posts, but first I want to tackle one simple non-adaptive theory that doesn&amp;#8217;t quite manage to do the&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why ageing is not (just) wear and&amp;nbsp;tear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The senescence of human organs consists not of their wearing out but of their lack of replacement when worn&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;George C. Williams, &amp;#8220;Pleiotropy, Natural Selection, and the Evolution of&amp;nbsp;Senescence&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One common folk theory of ageing is that it is simply wear and tear: like a car, the body is a machine, and like any machine it wears out over time. Exposure to the environment naturally leads to the accumulation of damage, which progressively impairs the function of the machine until it breaks down (i.e. we die). Any imperfection in the machine&amp;#8217;s components will hasten this process, either by generating more damage or by becoming progressively more dysfunctional over time. This progressive degradation is inevitable: we can keep a car in working order with regular maintenance and repair, but we are not (yet) capable of doing this for the kinds of wear and tear that accumulate in the body. Hence,&amp;nbsp;ageing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This explanation of ageing is intuitive, and parts of it are true as far as they go. There are certainly various kinds of damage and dysregulation that accumulate in the body with age: genetic mutations, senescent cells, shortened telomeres, cross-linked chemical aggregates, degraded stem-cell niches, and on and on. If we could remove and correct some or all of these issues the way we can replace a dodgy spark plug, we&amp;#8217;d go a long way towards addressing the problem of physiological&amp;nbsp;ageing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as an explanation of why ageing exists in the first place, &amp;#8220;wear and tear is inevitable&amp;#8221; just doesn&amp;#8217;t cut it, because a living body is not like a car. Where a car is dead matter shaped by external tools, a body is a dynamic, self-generating system with incredible powers of self-repair. These self-repair processes are awe-inspiringly good: of the &lt;em&gt;tens of thousands&lt;/em&gt; of genetic mutations that occur per cell every day in the human body, virtually all are accurately repaired. Our bodies can repair wounds, fight off infections, kill and replace malfunctioning cells, partially regrow (some) organs, even remodel their bones to best respond to the forces they experience. Many of these regenerative processes decline as we age, but that decline is itself part of the ageing process: young children are amazingly good at healing without scarring, for&amp;nbsp;example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while bodily damage is inevitable as part of the daily business of living, our bodies successfully repair almost all of it, especially when we&amp;#8217;re young. Evolutionarily speaking, the question is not why the damage occurs, but why it is &lt;em&gt;permitted to accumulate&lt;/em&gt;. It seems our bodies&amp;#8217; repair processes are not quite perfect, and allow damage and dysregulation to progressively accumulate over time. Why aren&amp;#8217;t they&amp;nbsp;better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could our bodies&amp;#8217; repair systems be better? They could certainly be worse: there are many, many mammal species with much shorter lifespans than humans&amp;#8217;, even when kept in very safe conditions. These animals age faster than humans because they accumulate damage and dysregulation faster; for whatever reason, their monitoring and repair systems have evolved to be that much sloppier than ours&lt;sup id="fnref:mrate"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:mrate"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Conversely, there are at least a few mammals (such as bowhead whales) that live longer than we do; clearly they have something going for them that we don&amp;#8217;t, but why? And that&amp;#8217;s without going into animals like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydra_viridissima"&gt;green hydra&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naked_mole-rat"&gt;naked mole rats&lt;/a&gt; that don&amp;#8217;t seem to age at all: if they can do it, why can&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it&amp;#8217;s not an evolutionary theory, wear-and-tear is incapable of addressing these questions. Yes, damage is inevitable, but why does this result in such different rates of ageing in different species? If one species can evolve to remove this damage so efficiently that it doesn&amp;#8217;t age at all, what is preventing most other species from doing the same? The answers to these questions don&amp;#8217;t lie in the eternal inevitability of molecular damage, but in the selective pressures each species is exposed to across evolutionary time. In the rest of this series, I&amp;#8217;ll address theories of ageing that attempt to explain ageing in these&amp;nbsp;terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:popage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, there&amp;#8217;s a fourth meaning that gets used in the media quite a lot: &amp;#8220;population ageing&amp;#8221;, by which is meant an increase in the median age of a population and the proportion of old people due to changes in social conditions. This is distinct from my &amp;#8220;demographic ageing&amp;#8221; in that the former is looking at the age composition of the whole population, while the latter is comparing different age groups within the population. I don&amp;#8217;t plan on talking about population ageing here.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:popage" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:mortality"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This increase in death rate is both intrinsic and extrinsic: older individuals are more likely to die from heart attack, stroke, cancer and so on, but are also more vulnerable to predation, starvation and disease.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:mortality" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:mrate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve left out an important consideration here, which is that rather than worse repair systems, these other mammals might be experiencing higher rates of damage, perhaps due to a higher metabolic rate. A repair system with the same stringency that is exposed to a higher level of damage will let more damage events through. Even if this is true, though, the question remains of why these animals haven&amp;#8217;t evolved better repair mechanisms to cope with this higher rate of damage.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:mrate" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:whales"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to being longer-lived than humans, bowhead whales are also larger. This also raises the classic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peto%27s_paradox"&gt;&amp;#8220;why don&amp;#8217;t all whales get cancer&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; problem: if cancer is a matter of mutations, mutations are a matter of chance, and whales have more cells in which the right mutations can accumulate, why don&amp;#8217;t they all get horrible tumours? There are various theories about this problem, too, none of which I intend to discuss here.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:whales" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="ageing"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="evolution"></category></entry></feed>